Shawn Achor:Good morning.I'm so excited to be here.
早上好 很高兴能给大家讲课
Tal is gone,which means that this morning I am the teacher
Tal走了 所以今天早上我来代课
for the defense against the dark arts,
给大家上"黑魔法防御术"
which I'm pretty sure
我很肯定 在这种情况下
makes me just as Dwight would say in The Office,
我可以套用美剧"办公室"里Dwight说的一句话
the assistant professor of positive psychology instead of
我是幸福课的助理教授
merely the assistant to the professor of positive psychology.
而不只是幸福课教授的助理
Many of you know me as head TF Shawn,or just Shawn,
很多人会叫我宿舍长TF Shawn 或者Shawn
or the Imzar of Kirkland House,or Mr.Positivity,
或者Kirkland的Imzar 或者幸福先生
or the guy who looks like a shizzle Roman god of War.
也有人叫我 那个像蹩脚罗马战神的家伙
But what many of you may not know is that
但你们很多人都不知道
I have a softer side too.
我也有温和的一面
When I was little,
小时候
I broke my sister's arms in 3 different places.
我给我妹妹的手臂弄了三处骨折
We were playing war and we were running around the living room,
我们在玩打仗 我们在客厅里到处跑
jumping over cushions as soldiers do.
像士兵一样 从坐垫上跳过去
And at one point of this conflict,as my report
打着打着 就像我后来…
which I filed to my parents later on clearly indicated that
写给我父母的检讨说的那样
I saw Cobra Commander takes a snap shot at my sister,
我看到眼镜蛇指挥官乱枪扫射我妹妹
with absolutely no regard for my own safety,
于是我不顾自己的安危
I reversed direction,dove head first into my sister,
我转过身 向我妹妹直冲过去
pushing her all the way out of the oncoming invisible bullet
推着她躲开那些射向我们的隐形子弹
and into a brick wall.
一直把她推到砖墙边
When my dad came into the room,
这时我爸爸走进客厅
I was standing above her,saying,"I'm a hero! I saved her!"
我站在她身边 说"我是英雄 我救了她"
Now does this make me a hero?
我真的成英雄了吗?
No.This doesn't make me...
没有 这样算不上英雄
You know who the real heroes are?
你知道真正的英雄是谁?
The real heroes are the people that wake up every day,
真正的英雄是那些每天醒过来
put on their ordinary clothes,go into their ordinary job,
穿上平凡的衣服 上平凡的班
get a distress call from the mayor,
接到市长的求助电话
put on their costume and go and fight crime.
穿上制服去抗击罪恶
Those are the real heroes.
这些才是真正的英雄
You know who's the hero? Hiro from the Heroes.
你知道谁是英雄吗? 电视剧"英雄"里的Hiro
Do you know where this is from?
你知道这句话从哪里来吗?
(Student: The Office!) The Office.Good.
"办公室" 很好
We have one person that watches comedy.Good.Thank you.
我们有一个同学看喜剧 很好 谢谢
I tell you the story because later that afternoon,
我之所以跟你们说这个故事 是因为那天下午
my sister and I were,after we went to the emergency room,
我妹妹和我 在我们去了急诊室回来后
we were playing on top of my bunk bed,and we were playing war.
我们在双层床上铺玩 我们又玩打仗了
We were slow learners.
我们还没学到教训
And this time it was my G.I.Joe against her my little ponies.
这一仗是我的特种部队 对抗她的小马
And in the midst of acting of this geopolitical conflict,
突然在这场地缘政治冲突中
my sister got really excited and leaned too far back on the bed.
我妹妹玩得很兴奋 往床外靠得太出了
As a result,
结果
she suddenly disappeared of the back of top of the bunk bed.
她突然从上铺上消失了
I looked over the side of the bunk bed,going,"not today."
我往双层床外一看 "怎么今天这么倒霉"
And I saw my sister there lying on the floor with her...
我看到我妹妹躺在地板上…
She landed painfully on her hands and knees on the floor.
她着地时 用手和膝盖痛苦地撑在地板上
And I saw this wail of suffering and pain
我看到她在痛苦 折磨
and injustice about to erupt out of my sister's mouth.
和不公中 正要大声哭出来
Now my parents have charged me
我父母已经交代过我
with playing as safely and as quietly as possible with my sister,
要和我妹妹玩得尽量安全 安静
seeing how I just broke her arm.
因为我刚刚弄断了她的手臂
And who are they gonna blame
他们会怪谁
if something happens to my sister again later on that day
如果那天再出事的是我妹妹
than the child that they love most,
而不是他们最爱的那个孩子
the one who they wanted to grow up to be a Ghostbuster,
那个他们希望长大后能当捉鬼敢死队员的孩子
the one who also broke her arm? Me.
那个弄断她手臂的孩子?当然是我
So I did the only thing
所以我说了
my frantic 7 year old brain can think to do,
我那个抓狂的7年级学生脑袋能想到的唯一一句话
and I said,"Amy,Amy,wait! Wait! Did you see how you landed?
我说"Amy 先别哭 你看到你刚才怎么着地的吗?
No human lands like that.You are a unicorn."
没有人类能那样着地 你是独角兽"
Now this was absolutely cheating,
当然这是骗她的
if I knew there was nothing in the world
因为我知道在这个世界上
my sister wanted more than for the rest of the world to realize
我妹妹最想要的就是让全世界的人都明白
that she was in fact a unicorn.
她其实是一头独角兽
And you can see on my sister's face this conflict as her brain
你可以从我妹妹的脸上看到她内心的挣扎
is tempted to devote resources to contemplating her new,
她的大脑想把精力用来关注她刚刚
contemplating her pain and suffering and injustice
带着骨折的手臂从双层床上掉下去而受到的
as she fell off her bed with a broken arm; or on the other side,
痛苦 折磨 和不公 但在另一方面
devoting resources to viewing the world
她的大脑又想把精力用来看看这个世界
and contemplating her new found identity as a unicorn.
关注她的新身份:一头独角兽
And the latter won out and a smile spread across my sister's face
后者胜出了 我妹妹脸上露出一个微笑
She laughed and she scrambled back on the bunk bed
她大笑起来 爬回双层床上
with all the grace of a baby unicorn.
带着一头小独角兽的优雅
Now what we realized is that
我们从中发现
this tender age of just 7 and 5 years old with something
5到7岁这个脆弱的年龄
that is going to be the heart
带有一些特征
as the vanguard of the positive psychology revolution
这些特征将会成为幸福心理学革命的核心
that we've been talking about,
这个我们已经讲过了
about how our brain is basically a single processor,
我们讲过我们的大脑就像一个单一处理器
capable of consciously choosing to devote resources
能够有意识地选择把精力放在
either to the pain and suffering on one side,
痛苦和折磨上 或者把精力用来
or viewing the world
用乐观
that lens of something like optimism or mindfulness.
和正念的眼光 来看这个世界
So too I think humor is exactly in this the facet.
所以我觉得幽默也正是这样
I think that humor itself is the option,
我认为幽默本身就是一种选择
the mindful option of choosing between viewing the world
有意地去选择 怎样来看待世界
through the lens of being,of suffering,of optimism-
是用痛苦 乐观…
suffering,not optimism,suffering,of pain,of injustice,
是痛苦 不是乐观 用痛苦 折磨 不公的眼光来看这个世界
or viewing the world
还是用一种
through the lens of something of adaptive and powerful.
适应性的强有力的眼光来看
So today I actually bought a new one of these
这个其实是我今天新买的
cause the other one didn't work.
因为旧的那个用不了
Because I didn't turn on the power.
因为我没有打开电源
So I defined humor today as a mindful lens,
今天我把幽默定义为一种正念的眼光
through which we can view the world
通过幽默 我们可以用
as a way of mindfully perceiving the world,
正念的眼光看待世界
analogous to optimism,
就像乐观主义那样
where an individual heightens awareness
这时一个人会提高
of potentials within a situation.
对一种情况的各种可能的意识
Today we are going to talk about
今天我们会讲
a lot of different definitions of happiness
对幸福的很多种不同的定义
and different ways that we can perceive of it
以及我们看待幸福的不同角度
and the effects upon all of us.
及其对我们的影响
But before we do so,I wanna talk a little bit
在讲之前 我想说说
about why we are doing this in the first place.
我们为什么要讲这些
First of all,Tal knew that he's going to be away today.
首先 Tal知道他今天不能来上课
He told me repeatedly in March that there's no way
他三月时告诉过我很多次 他没办法
he's going to teach during the Tuesday after 420 which I just,
星期二下午4点20分以后上课
I assume he meant because of the Passover.
我想他的意思是因为逾越节的关系
And so I agreed to give a talk on humor because it seems that
所以我同意上一节关于幽默的课 因为我觉得
it seams through the proverbial cracks of the assigned readings
它能把这门课布置的各种阅读资料
and syllabus for this course.
以及课程大纲 很好地衔接起来
If you are unaware that there are assigned readings
如果你不知道这门课有布置阅读
and a syllabus for this course,
和课程大纲的话
you talk to me after class.
下课后来找我
So I'm sure that
所以我很肯定
Tal was said to not be here this week and last weekend,
Tal这周和上周末都不会来学校
cause he missed to see the Wu-Tang Clan
因为他很想去看"武当派"乐队
and Gavin Degraw reunited at last.
Gavin Degraw终于让它团聚了
Did you guys see the Crimson article from yesterday
你们看到昨天Crimson的文章吗
that described how one of the members of Wu-Tang Clan,
讲武当派的一个成员
an unidentified member of Wu-Tang Clan held out his microphone
一个不知名的武当派成员 在音乐会上
at one point during the concert for the rest of the audience to,
拿出他的麦克风 让观众们
just infer them to do the lyrics,to finish the lyrics for him.
让他们帮他唱完歌词
And what he was met was a stony stone silence.
结果全场鸦雀无声
He responded,
他见状说
"well I guess you guys aren't as smart as you thought you were."
"看来你们都没有自己以为的那么聪明"
You know you hit the rock bottom
当一个不知名的武当派成员
when an unidentified member of Wu-Tang Clan is making fun of you.
嘲笑你时 你就知道你跌到谷底了
So I'm excited about being here today for several reasons.
我今天很高兴来上课 这是有几个原因的
First of all,I think humor
首先 我认为幽默
is one of the most important part of the positive psychology
是我们将要讲到的幸福心理学
that we'll be talk about,because
最重要的一部分 因为
it matters at every single level of things that we describe.
它在我们说的每件事上都占了重要地位
If you know me,you'll know that I went here as an undergraduate-
如果大家了解我的话 大家应该知道我本科在哈佛读
I studied English and religion,went to the Divinity School
我学英语和宗教 我当时上神学院
when I studied Christian and Buddhist Ethics.
学习基督教和佛教伦理
And now I moved to study psychology
现在我转学心理学
and running a positive psychology
还在Kirkland宿舍外23号滩
consulting firm out of Kirkland beach 23.
开了一间幸福心理咨询公司
And I'm also the sort of intramural tutor/legends/national hero
我还是Kirkland宿舍的校内指导员 传奇人物
in Kirkland house.
和国家英雄
I'm very important.I'm very important.
我是重要人物
I've many leather bound books
我有很多皮订书
and my room smells a rich mahogany.
我的房间一股红木家具的味道 很像有钱人
It also looks a lot like a dorm.
看起来很像一间宿舍
I tell you this because I'm running out things to say
我跟你们说这些 是因为我找不到话说了
and this synthesis of religion and psychology and English
这个宗教 心理 英语
and philosophy well all play an important part
和哲学的综合知识将会在今节课
in today's lecture.
发挥重要作用
So today,very quickly the things that we'll talk about:
我简单介绍一下今天会讲的内容
we'll talk about psychology of humor;
我们会讲幽默心理
we are going to talk about the mental
我们会讲幽默
and physical benefits of humor;
对心理和生理的益处
we'll talk about the positive social benefits,
我们会讲幽默的积极社会影响
pragmatic steps that you can take on your own
你们自己培养幽默感的实用方法
and the greatest power of humor
以及幽默最强大的功效
which is I believe the therapeutic value of humor,
我认为那就是幽默的心理治疗价值
the ability to view the world in a completely different way
通过改变我们的认知心态 用一种完全不同的
by changing our cognitive mindsets.
方法看待世界的能力
Now many of you know that
很多同学都知道
I'm responsible for writing much of the final.
大部分期末试卷考题都是我出的
I'm also a slow reader.
而且我评卷看得很慢
This combination means
这两个因素结合起来 意味着
the majority of the final will be probably on this lecture.
期末考试大部分内容可能会出自这堂课
So I'll definitely point out the parts of the lecture
所以我一定会指出这节课
that you absolutely need to write down
有哪些内容是你们一定要写下来的
which surely must be extremely copious notes from this morning.
而且今早的课一定会有大量的笔记
So let me tell you about C I know you are sitting there,
我告诉大家…我知道你们坐在那里
looking at my PowerPoint slides and thinking yourself,
看着我的幻灯片想
"I'm probably gonna name my first three children Shawn
"我前三个孩子都会取命为Shawn
regardless of gender.
不管是男孩还是女孩
And I wonder what it is
不知道是什么
that got Shawn in psychology in the first place."
驱使Shawn学心理学的"
Well I'll tell you so you can concentrate,
我会告诉大家 好让你们能专心听课
but it also serves as a case study for us today.
也可以作为今天的一个案例
I fell in love with psychology
我爱上心理学
when I fell in love with my babysitter.
是当我爱上照顾我的保姆时
With my babysitters.
不止一个保姆
All of my babysitters came from my dad's psychology class.
我的保姆都是我爸爸心理班的学生
He taught psychology in Bell University.
他在贝尔大学教心理学
So all of my babysitters came from his classes.
所以我的保姆都是那个班上的
And I fell in love with all of them.
我爱上了她们全部
And I realized at one point that
有一天我发现
the dating wasn't going as well as I hoped to C
这种约会没有我希望的那么顺利
we were only dating whenever my parents paid for it.
因为只有我父母付钱时 我们才能约会
And so I decided to take matters in my own hand.
所以我决定自己来解决这个问题
And I decided that the only way
我决定我能和这些女孩
that I could possibly date these girls
约会的唯一方法
was to be part of their world for a little bit.
就是进入她们的世界
I took this advice from Ariel of the Little Mermaid.And
这招我是从"海的女儿"里的小美人鱼学来的
so I decided to volunteer to be part of a psychology experiment
所以我决定当我爸爸班上的一个心理实验的
in my dad's class.
自愿者
And he was really excited about having me there,
他很高兴我会去他的班
so he invited me on the day
所以当他们班上
when they have the brainwave machine in class
准备了脑波机那天 他请我去他班上
and they are hooking people up to it.
他们会把人连接上那台机器
And I thought this would an excellent way for me
我觉得这个好方法能让我给那些女孩
to impress these girls.
留下深刻印象
Because nothing is as attractive like an electrodes lube
因为没什么能比头上涂了电极润滑油
on your head and with all these wires hanging off.
还连着各种各样的电线更吸引人了
It's just as hot today as it was then.
那天和今天一样热
So anyway I was there,and I was smiling,
总之我去到班上 我在笑着
because they were all smiling at me.
因为她们都朝我笑
And I thought things were going pretty well on our date so far.
我觉得这个约会进展得还不错
When all of a sudden,my dad was so excited -
突然 我爸爸因为太激动了
he forgot to do something very simple.
他忘了做一件很简单的事
And it was a rudimentary machine because this was a while ago.
那是很久以前的事了 那台机器很原始
He forgot to ground the wire on the brainwave machine.
他忘了给脑波机接地线
So the very first thing that happened to me was a C
所以我马上就遭到…
on our date,was I got an electroshock.
在我们的约会上 我被电击了
I was like,"Shut it off!"
我当时这样叫"把它关掉"
Everyone burst into laughter
大家都大笑起来
including all of my future toward love affairs with these women.
我和这些女人的未来恋情也都泡汤了
And my dad was laughing so hard that he was crying.
我爸爸笑到流眼泪
He couldn't even help me.
他笑都连帮都帮不了我
He was able to shove the machine.
他能关掉机器
But that's about it.
但他没有
And I guess he thought it was pretty funny.
他可能觉得这样很好笑
I guess cruel and unusual punishments were pretty funny I guess.
也许残酷而不同寻常的惩罚是很好笑
Maybe water boarding next time,dad.Thanks a lot.
爸爸 不如下次用水刑吧 谢谢你
So I'd love to be part of your experiments again.
我很喜欢再参加你的实验
So anyway I was so embarrassed and so upset.
总之 我很尴尬 很生气
I ripped off all of my electrodes one by one,
我一个一个都拔掉所有电极
while everyone was laughing at me,
当时大家都在笑我
and stalked off the side of the classroom.
我从教室边上昂首挺胸地走出
And right as I get to the door,fortunately,
当我走到门前时 幸好
I turned back and said,
我转过身说
"dad,thanks a lot for ruining my chance with all my girlfriends,"
"爸爸 谢谢你毁了我和这些女朋友发展的机会"
and then slammed the door.
然后摔门而去
And it's true.I never did get any of these girls.
这是真的 那些女孩我一个都没追到
So what just happened there?
刚才那是怎么回事?
For the few of you that did laugh at the story,
那几个听到这个故事大笑的同学
what was it that C it's weird.
这是什么…真奇怪
Thing is that the acoustic is building incredible
这个教室的音效设备真好
like you can hear the laughter that is going on all the time.
你总是能听到笑声
It's amazing.It's like the room is eating my laughter.
太厉害了 就像这个教室能吞掉我的笑声一样
So what just happened there?
刚才那是怎么回事?
Well I think that one of the things that's really interesting
我想很有趣的一件事是
is that you laugh at the story
你们之所以听到这个故事会笑
because it's couched not as a story of tragedy
因为我说的不是一个悲剧
but it's a story of love and child abuse.
而是一个充满爱的虐童故事
And we laugh because this is a moment
我们之所以笑 是因为这一刻
in which we've been primed to laugh,
我们都做好了笑的准备
or surrounded by a group of people who,
或者说 我们周围都是人
we are probably laughing because we are a roomful of people.
我们笑 很可能是因为我们有一大班人
Groups have a social effect upon us,right?
群体对我们有社会影响 对吧?
So if you want to hide a sensation,please feel free
如果你想隐藏感情 请尽管
to hold the hands with the person sitting next to you.
拉住坐在你旁边的同学的手
But the interesting thing is when you laugh,
但有趣的是 当你笑时
laughter itself is so weird.
笑声很怪异
Wikipedia defines humor as
维基百科把幽默定义为
"the rhythmic,vocalized,expiratory and involuntary actions",
"一种有节奏的发声的不由自主呼吸动作"
which is I also hire to define as much of my dancing.
这也是我对我的舞姿的定义
But when you are laughing and right now,
但当你笑时 就像现在
15 facial muscles in your body are going crazy,
你身体有15块面部肌肉 在疯狂地运动
including your zygomatic major muscle
包括你的大颧肌
which is raising your lips at the same time.
它能同时拉起你的嘴唇
This is pretty cool.I have no idea how this happens.
非常酷 我不知道它的原理是什么
But epiglottis starts to cover over your larynx,
会厌软骨开始盖住你的喉
which makes constricting your breathing,
这样就收缩了你的呼吸
which means you are basically suffocating,
所以基本上你是在窒息
which is why you are having trouble catching your breath.
这就是为什么笑的时候很难呼吸
You are welcome.
别怪我引你们笑
Blood pressure is lowered,while at the same time somehow
血压降低 同时
you have an increased vascular blood flow
血管里血液的流量增大
and you flex your abdominal,
腹部肌肉伸缩
respiratory,facial,leg,and back muscles.
呼吸 脸部 腿和后背的肌肉都会伸缩
This is the most work out I've ever had.Ever.
这是我做过最强烈的健身运动
Now this is amazing that this would happen.
这一切发生得太神奇了
And it's clear
很显然
that humor and laughter has a visceral effect upon us.
幽默和笑声会对我们产生情感的影响
It clearly has social effect C
很明显它有社会影响
if you are in a good mood right now,
如果你现在心情好
chances are you could be laughing more;
你可能会笑得更多
if you are in a bad mood right now,
如果你现在心情不好
chances are you can't help laughing at my joke.
你可能听到我的笑话 会忍不住大笑
So part of what's going on here is that the social environment,
所以这当中的几个作用因素 是社会环境
the room,the jokes themselves,
教室 还有笑话本身
your physical body are all manifesting changes because of this.
我的身体因此而表现出变化
The question is then C can we study humor
问题是 你能研究幽默吗
just as we ask the question "can we study happiness?"
就像我们问的那个问题"你能研究幸福吗?"一样
And what's the point of studying humor?
研究幽默有什么用?
Well,just as Tal mentioned that
就像Tal讲过的那样
right now there's a either 17 to 1 or 21 to 1
现在的学术期刊上
negative to positive ratio of research
消极研究与积极研究的比例是
that is occurring in the scholar journals.
17比1 或者21比1
Last night when I supposed to be writing this talk,
昨晚我写这节课的讲义时
I looked on the e-resources and
我在eResources上查东西
found that there's a 97 to 3 ratio of negative to humor research.
我发现消极研究与幽默研究的比例是97比3
For example,depression was 125,000 articles,
例如 研究抑郁症的有125000篇文章
while humor was only 4,943 articles.
而研究幽默的只有4943篇
Nothing came up for "Steven Colbert".
搜索Steven Colbert时 结果为零
But the reason why that this is important
这其中有一个重要原因
is because of something called Medical School Syndrome.
因为一种叫医学院症候群的现象
We know that
我们知道
the way we study absolutely has effects upon our body.
我们的学习对我们的身体是绝对有影响的
So if you know that the Medical School Syndrome,
所以如果你知道医学院症候群
you'll know that
你就会知道
as doctors are learning about all the different diseases
当医生对世界上各种疾病的知识
that are out there in the world,
越来越丰富时
suddenly they realize they have all of them.
他们会突然发现 自己好像什么病都患上了
And my brother in law called me from medical school
我妹夫从医学院打电话给我
and said,"Shawn," C my brother in law's name is Bobo.
他说"Shawn" 我妹夫名字叫Bobo
That's another story.
这是题外话了
Bobo called me from medical school,
Bobo从医学院打电话给我
and said,"Shawn I have leprosy."
他说"Shawn 我患麻风了"
And I had no idea how to console him
我不知道怎么安慰他
because he just got over a menopause.
因为他刚刚才过完更年期
The way we study the world around us actually changes the lens
我们研究世界的视角 真的能改变
through which we view the world.
我们看待世界的视角
And if we are not studying humor,
如果我们不研究幽默
we are missing out one of the major aspects
我们就不会了解社会互动的
of social interactions,
一个重大方面
but also the way that the world works.
也无法了解世界是怎么运行的
So why don't we talk about humor more often?
那为什么我们对幽默的研究这么少?
First of all,humor is extremely difficult to define.
首先 幽默是非常难定义的
Every time you are tempted to define humor,
每次你想定义幽默
it seems to slip through your fingers.
它就从你的指间溜走
Every time you try... Everyone finds something else funny,right?
每次你想…大家觉得好笑的东西都不一样
What I wanted to show for videos today,
例如我今天想放的视频
you might not find funny at all.
你们可能会觉得一点都不好笑
And what you find funny is objectively not funny at all.
你们觉得好笑的地方 客观来说一点都不好笑
I tried to show my parents Superbad
我想让我父母看"太坏了"
cause I thought that was funny.
因为我觉得那部电影很好笑
And if they are laughing on the inside,
但就算他们心里觉得好笑
they certainly weren't showing on the outside.
他们也不会笑出来
Part of what we were doing C
一部分是…
you know some people laugh at things serious
有些人听到严肃的事会笑
that are supposed to be serious,like Gossip Girl.
或者说本应该很严肃的事 例如"绯闻女孩"
And then people on the Kirkland -
Kirkland宿舍的人
Kirkland girl have to throw pillows at them
kirkland宿舍的女同学 要用枕头打她们
and threaten to ad-board them just so I don't miss anything.
威胁把她们登在广告栏上 才能让她们笑出来
So why I talk about... So part of it is the definitional problems.
所以我为什么说…研究幽默的难点之一就是定义
It's so difficult for us actually define what humor is,
我们很难定义幽默是什么
because the moment you begin to define it,
因为当你一定义它
it seems to slip through fingers.
它就从指间溜走了
The moment you are tempted to explain to somebody,
当你想向别人解释
explain to your e-harmony date
向你交友网eHarmony上的对象解释
why you are much funnier than they think you are,
为什么你比她们想象中的更幽默时
you already know
你就知道
you've gone down the wrong path for a lot of different reasons.
不管怎样看 你都走错方向了
But part of what we are seeing here is that
我们从中发现
once we are tempted to define something,
一旦我们试图去定义某些东西
once we attempt to define what makes something humorous,
一旦我们试图定义是什么让一些事情变得幽默时
it immediately seems to go away.
这些事情马上就不幽默了
This is the Dead Frog Problem.
这是一个死青蛙问题
The Dead Frog Problem is that
死青蛙问题就是说
the more you seem to dissect the frog,the faster it seems to die
你越是解剖一只青蛙 它死得就越快
The same is true with a joke.
笑话也如此
And as a result of this,
因此
that makes it very difficult for us to study it.
这使得幽默很难研究
But let's say even if we could study it.
即使我们能研究它
Let's say we could study it.
假设我们能研究它
We know it has physical and social benefits.
我们知道它对我们的身体和社交有益处
That doesn't do us a world of good
但如果有些人天生就是幽默的
if people are just naturally funny
有些人天生就是不幽默的
and some people are unnaturally funny.
就算研究它也帮不了我们什么
If you are just genetically funny,if you are born funny,
如果你天生就幽默
and we all think that there are certain people that are like that
我们认为确实有些人是天生幽默的
if you think that some people are born funny,
如果你认为幽默是天生的
that doesn't do us any good to talk about the benefits
这样就知道它有什么益处 对我们也没什么帮助
that none of us can access.
因为我们都得不到这些益处
It's the same way with positive psychology,right?
这跟幸福心理是一样的道理 对吧?
It's the same problem we have with positive and happy
在研究积极 幸福
and optimistic people C they are just annoying.
乐观的人是 也有同样的问题 他们太莫名其妙了
But part of what we are seeing is,
但我们可以看到
that part of our worry is that while we are studying this,
我们研究幸福心理的一个担心是
if happiness,positivity and optimism are all based upon genetics
如果幸福 积极 和乐观都是由基因决定的
then there's no point of studying any of the things
那么研究我们在这个班上所讲的内容
we've been talking about so far in this class.
还有什么意义?
The same is true with humor.
幽默也是如此
If we can't access any of those benefits,
如果我们得不到这些益处
that just gives the funny people more to laugh at us about.
只会给幽默的人更多理由来嘲笑我们
So I think we can overcome all the barriers today.
我想我们今天能克服所有这些障碍
And I think there are some extraordinary research
我知道幸福心理领域已经出版了
that has been coming out in positive psychology
一些非常棒的研究
and research specifically on humor
还有专门研究幽默的研究
that's actually going to allow us
这些研究能让我们
to be able to look at this human phenomena in a way
用全新的角度来研究幽默这个人类现象
that actually is gonna help us in a lot of different ways.
并且给我们带来各种各样的益处
So let me tell you that there is actually -
所以我想告诉大家 我们有…
in order to study this just as we did with positive psychology,
为了让我们能够像研究幸福心理一样研究幽默
we are going to have to look at
我们要看看
where we looked at the humanist tradition of psychology.
心理学的人文传统
So too we are going to ground ourselves
所以我们要立足于
in the philosophies of humor.
幽默的哲学
We are gonna have to understand the giants of humor.
我们会讲到研究幽默的三大巨人
And we are gonna look at two of the theories
我们还会讲两个理论
which I don't find one of them more compelling than the other.
我觉得这两个理论 没有什么高低之分
What I find really compelling is my explanation
真正高明的是我的解释
which I shall be giving afterwards.
我稍后就会讲给大家听
So basically there are three giants
这三大巨人
in the field of psychological research on humor-
研究幽默这个心理学领域的三大巨人
Sigmund Freud,Henri Bergson,and me.
就是弗洛伊德 伯格森 和我
And so we'll first talk about Sigmund Freud.
我们先来讲弗洛伊德
Sigmund Freud whose surely unassailable logical assumptions on
弗洛伊德他在很多课题上 都作出过无懈可击的
the whole host of topics will absolutely stand the test of time.
符合逻辑的假设 而且这些假设都将经受得起时间的考验
Wrote a book called Jokes
他写了一本书叫
and Their Relationship to the Unconscious.
《笑话及其与潜意识的关系》
Jokes and Their Relationship to the Unconscious -
if you haven't read it - is for a guy writing a book about humor,
如果你还没有看过 对于写一本关于幽默的书的人来说
this is the most unfunny collection of stories since Leviticus.
这本书是自《利末记》以来最不好笑的笑话集
And in this book he describes this model consciousness
在这本书里 他描述了一种典范意识
while the inside you have the id - the id contains the sexual
在我们内心有一个本我 这个本我包括了大家都有的
and the physical and the violent impulses that we all have.
性欲 生命力 和冲动
I don't have,cause I went to the Divinity School,
我没有 因为我读过神学院
but you all have.
但你们都有
Outside of that is the ego which makes the decisions about the id
本我之外 是自我 这个自我会把本我视为
as the permeable barrier between the id impulses and the society.
本我冲动和社会之间一道可渗透的屏障
And the outside layer is super-ego.
最外面的是超我
The super-ego is the moral constraints,
超我是加在我们身上的
the societal constraints that is placed upon us.
道德约束和社会约束
So for example,if my id impulse make,
例如 如果我的本我冲动
means that I'm angry at you,and I want to punch you,
说我很生气 我想揍你
my super-ego,the constraints of society prevent me from doing so
我的超我 那个道德约束就会阻止我打你
And in the same way if I was wanting to have sex with somebody
同样 如果我想和某个人上床
and my super-ego said that it was not OK.
我的超我说这样不行
The super-ego,
超我
the moral constraints of society would prevent me from having sex
这个社会道德约束会阻止我和别人上床
That's probably the only thing keeping me from having sex.
这可能是唯一能阻止我上床的东西了
It's my super-ego.
我的超我
And so one of the things that we find
我们发现
is that Freud argues we get frustrated.
弗洛伊德说的是 我们都会受挫
We get frustrated because those id impulses are there
我们都会受挫 因为我们都有本我冲动
but we have no way of getting those impulses out into the world.
但我们没办法把这些冲动释放出来
And so we become repressed.
所以我们就会被压抑
And more you become repressed,
你越压抑
I think something's about exploding in the end.
最终就会爆发
So there's something that's really bad about that.
所以压抑会带来严重后果
So what he says is that humor is a socially acceptable envelope
他认为 幽默是一种社会可接受的
for couching those id desires.
用来疏导这些欲望的信封
It's a way,a socially acceptable way
这是一种社会可接受的
of getting those id impulses out into society,which explains
把本我冲动释放出来的方法 这就解释了
why so much of our humor is sexual or aggressive in nature.
为什么我们很多幽默 本质上都是与性和攻击有关的
There's a lot of different examples that we can talk about this-
我们可以举很多例子来说明
that humor as a psychological safety vault,
把幽默视为一个心理保险库
is one of the ways which explains
这就解释了
why you have sexual innuendo jokes on the first date,right?
为什么你们会在首次约会时说一些隐晦的黄段子 对吧?
Before physicality might be socially acceptable,
在我们的体格特征得到社会接受前
which also explains Michael Scott from the Office -
这也解释了"办公室"里Michael Scott说的那个
"that's what she said" jokes,
"她是这样说的"笑话
where he says "that's what she said" to everything.
他不管什么事都说"她是这样说的"
While some of them are pretty hard to understand,and slippery,
他有些笑话很隐晦
and hard to grasp,they always left me smiling and satisfied.
很难领会 但我每次听到都笑而不语 心满意足
So this also explains humor we have toward political figures.
这也解释了我们为什么喜欢拿政治人物来开玩笑
A lot of time when political figures were not able to,
很多时候 政治人物不能…
we have no recourse at the sexual aggressive level
因为我们无法通过性行为
to vent our frustration.
来发泄这种挫折感
So humor is actually one of the ways we can get that out there.
所以我们就会通过幽默来表达对政治的不满
The humor itself using words is the way that
通过语言上的幽默
we can allow for id impulses to come out.
我们能够允许冲动释放出来
Because those words
因为这些话
don't violate very many of our social constructions.
不会破坏我们大部分的社会结构
We'll talk about that in a moment -
我们等一下会再讲到这一点
one of the flaws with Freud theory.
弗洛伊德理论的缺陷之一
But supposedly the words don't actually harm us.
正常来说 言语伤不了人
So it's socially acceptable.
它是社会可接受的
Steven Colbert says that six stones may break my bones,
Steven Colbert说六块石头就能砸碎我的骨头
but words will never hurt me,
但言语永远伤不了我
unless you throw a dictionary at me.
除非你拿本字典砸我
Write that down.That's important.Write that down.
写下这句 这句很重要 写下来
Henri Bergson is the second giant in the field of humor research.
亨利・伯格森是幽默研究领域的第二大巨人
Henri Bergson,which I'm definitely saying right
亨利・伯格森 我肯定没念错
with the French accent combined with a Texan.
因为我用法语口音再加上我的德州口间念的
I think Henri Berg... I think you- with French you drop everything.
这个名字的发音…念法语可以省念很多音
And... Really? That one was funny? All right.
真的话? 这句你们都觉得好笑? 好的
Humor as a social "corrective" - he argues that
他认为幽默是一种社会纠正器 他认为…
just like Abraham Maslow who is studied earlier in the class,
就像以前上过这门课的Abraham Maslow说过
is that humans are under developmental trajectory
人是有一个发展轨迹的
toward self-actualization or achieving our potential.
终点是自我实现 或者说实现我们的潜力
And what Bergson argues is that humor is the point
伯格森认为 幽默就是轨迹上的一个点
in which we correct somebody
在一个点上 当我们偏离这条轨迹时
when we slip or fall off this developmental trajectory,
当我们做一些阻碍我们自我实现的事时
when we do something that doesn't allow us to self-actualize
幽默就会马上
as fast as we could.
纠正我们
Comedian Lewis Black for example talks about children
例如 喜剧演员Lewis Black这样说那些
who go during the summer to Harry Potter Quidditch camps
参加哈利波特魁地奇夏令营
and ride around on brooms and throw Frisbees -
骑着个扫把 玩飞盘的孩子
I can't say it - Frisbees at each other.
我念不对 跟玩伴玩飞盘
And what he says is to gently chide these children C
他其实是拐了个弯来骂这些孩子
he said these children
他说 这群怪小孩
might as well start crying about the prom now.
现在就该开始为毕业舞会找不到舞伴发愁了
What he is doing there is,as we've done something maladaptive
他的意思是 当我们做了一些不利于适应的事时
like going to a Harry Potter Quidditch camp
例如去参加哈利波特魁地奇夏令营
or paying 14 dollars for a drink at Om
或者花14美元去Om喝杯酒
or actively enjoying an econometrics or landlord theory
或者打心底里喜欢经济计量学或者地主理论
or actually ordering food at the Hong Kong lounge and restaurant.
或者在香港俱乐部和餐厅订餐
In all these situations,
在这些情况下
we laugh at individuals in order to correct them,
我们笑这些人 是为了纠正他们
to prevent them from falling off this development trajectory
阻止他们偏离这条发展轨迹
so that they can continue on toward self-actualization.
这样他们就能继续迈向自我实现的目标
If somebody calls,if my girlfriend calls,if my girlfriend,-
如果有人打电话来 如果我女朋友打来…
I was hoping it would get a clap.
我还希望大家能给点掌声
I knew this wasn't odd.At least no one was laughing.
我就知道大家都不觉得奇怪我有女朋友 至少没人笑
So if a girlfriend calls her boyfriend
如果一个女朋友打给电话给她男朋友
to leave a scandalous junk dial message,
留了一段不雅的留言
and accidentally leaves this junk dial message
意外地这段留言
on her boyfriend's father's work line,
留到她男朋友父亲的电话上了
we laugh in order to correct those mistakes.
我们都会大笑 为了纠正这样的错误
Another story that I heard in Kirkland was somebody
另一个我在Kirkland宿舍听说的笑话是 有一个人
who for Halloween dressed up with a making a dress
在万圣节那天穿了一件
completely out of magazine articles from Cosmo using duck tape
用Cosmo杂志的文章和胶带做成的裙子
and went out on the freezing cold,
在大冷天走出去
slipped and fell on the ice on her butt and tore the dress.
滑了一跤 屁股掉到冰面上 裙子撕破了
And I don't even know where to begin with that one.
这个故事有太多值得我们笑的地方
But part of the reason that we laugh is that
但我们会笑的原因之一是
we all fall through developmental trajectory at some point.
我们有时都会偏离发展轨迹
And I believe that it was Plato who said that
我记得柏拉图说过
the magazine dresses will not help us self-actualize any faster.
杂志裙子不能帮我们更快地达到自我实现
So we've looked at two different things:
我们已经讲了两个内容了
we've looked at humor as a corrective,
我们讲了幽默是一种纠正器
and we looked humor as a psychology release.
我们讲了幽默是一种心理释放
I think one of the people that's absolutely brilliant
我个人觉得在研究幽默作为社会纠正器
in the field of research on humor
这个领域中
as a social corrective is one of the giants I think myself -
有一个非常聪明的人 他就是三巨人之一
no one says that - is Dale Sturtevant.
这是我自己评的 他就是Dale Sturtevant
Dale Sturtevant is somebody that
Dale Sturtevant是一个
you definitely want to write down in your notes.
你们绝对需要在笔记本里记下来的人
And fortunately thanks to the magic of YouTube,
很幸运 多亏有了神奇的Youtube
we are gonna get to see Dale Sturtevant's approach to psychology.
你们能看到Dale Sturtevant是怎么研究心理学的
[VIDEO: Dale Sturtevant]
I'm Dale Sturtevant.
我是Dale Sturtevant
I've been raising dogs since I was six.
我六岁起就养狗
And nothing has brought me more joy,
没什么能比训练小狗给我带来
or more sheer frustration,than training a puppy.
更多的快乐和挫败感
With a very young pup,
养一只小狗
correcting problem behavior can be especially maddening.
纠正它不正确的行为尤其让人恼火
And,like you,
像你一样
I've probably tried all the tricks - screaming myself hoarse,
我试过所有的办法 骂到声音嘶哑
starving them,locking them in a closet for days on end,
不给东西它们吃 把它们锁在柜子里连续几天
or just beating them without mercy.
或者毫不留情地打它们
But after my third arrest
但在我第三次被气得心脏病发
and court-ordered anger-management counseling,
和上了一个法庭强制的控制愤怒心理治疗后
I learned to channel my rage
我学会了把我的愤怒
into an effective non-violent puppy training tool.
转化为一个有效非暴力的训练手段
It's called "Dissing Your Dog:
这个手段叫"鄙视你的狗
how to train your puppy with mockery and verbal humiliation".
如何用讽刺和口头羞辱来训练你的小狗"
You see,
你们看
dogs are much more intuitive than we give them credit for.
狗要比我们想象中的更聪明
They know when they're the butt of ridicule.
它们知道自己什么时候被人嘲笑
And when they misbehave,
当它们不听话时
a well-placed sarcastic comment or cutting remark
一句到位的讽剌 或者一句伤人的话
can work wonders wherever a rolled-up newspaper fails.
就能达到一根打狗棒达不到的效果
Whatever your puppy's behavior problem,
不管你的小狗有什么行为问题
I guarantee I can help you fix it.
我保证可以帮你纠正
Problems like jumping on furniture.
例如 跳到沙发上
Oh no,no,no,Humphrey,don't get up.
不 Humphrey 别起来
Why don't you just stay there,relax? After all,
你应该躺在上面休息 毕竟
you did put in a long day of work at a demanding high-stress job.
你在一份要求高压力大的工作中忙了一整天
Oh no,wait a minute,that's me!
不 慢着 那应该是我才对
Now I remember! I'm the one with the job.
我想起来了 我才是要工作的那个人
You're the one who lies around the house all day
你只是一条整天在家里躺着
in a pool of your own slobber!
流了满地口水的狗
Accidents in the house.
在家里大小便
"Hey,Walter! Thanks for your ‘help' with the new off-white sofa.
"Walter 多亏你"帮忙"装饰了这张米白色新沙发
Everybody agrees that dump you left there
大家都说你拉在上面的那堆东西
was the perfect 'accent'.
给了它一个完美的"点缀"
So,good job.Oh,and by the way,Milton Berle called.
做得好 对了 Milton Berle打过电话来
He wants his bladder control back.That's it! Good dog!"
他想要回他的膀胱控制器 这就对了 真乖"
Fussy eating habits.
挑食
"Oh,right,Margaret,you wanted a prime rib.
"对 Margaret 你想吃的是顶级排骨
Here's the deal: The Palm wasn't taking reservations,
事情是这样的:Palm餐厅不接受订位
and I didn't even try Morton's
我没试过打去Morton's餐馆订位
because I understand they have a new chef.
因为我知道他们换了新大厨
So for now,let's just go with the Alpo,okay?
所以现在 你就吃Alpo狗粮吧 好吗?
I know it's not your first choice but keep in mind,
我知道这不是你的第一选择 但别忘了
you're a f--king dog! "
你只是一条狗!"
Shawn:Tears come to my eyes at this modern day Marva Collins.
这个现代卓别林让我笑得流眼泪
So why do we look at this series?
为什么我们看这段视频?
Why do we study these philosophies? How do they help us?
我们为什么要学习这两个理论?它们对我们有什么帮助?
Well,they don't,because they are both wrong.
其实它们帮不了我们 它们都是错的
And the reason that it is wrong is they missed the part of the,
它们错的原因是 他们忽略了一个
part about humor that
幽默的特征
I think is most important and my explanation for it.
我们认为这个特征是最重要的 我的解释也很重要
\fe1\fnCalibri\fs15\b1\bord2\shad0\fsp0\c&H0ffffff&So oh you don't have to write all of this down at once -
你们不用马上全部记下来
pretended it slowly coming out.
假装PPT上的东西是慢慢地出来的
So I believe that humor is a mindful lens
我认为幽默就像一种正念视角
through which we view the world.
我们透过这个视角来看待世界
And part of the way that we can see that is that
我们研究这点的一个角度是
we can see that humor itself is the cognitive lens
我们可以把幽默视为一种认知心态
through which we view actions that come into our environment.
我们通过它看待我们周围发生的事
We can see this by asking question
要研究这个问题 我们可以问
of why is that some people find humor in situations
为什么一些别人认为不好笑 或者很悲剧的事情
where some people see something as neutral or sad or tragic.
有些人会从中看到幽默?
Right? Why is it that some people can find things
为什么有些人觉得好笑的东西
that can be funny where other people can't?
别人会觉得不好笑?
And the same way that somebody
同样道理 为什么
who is optimistic can find something that is good in a situation,
乐观的人能在一件事中看到好的一面
where somebody who's in a neutral state,or pessimistic state,
而不悲不乐的人 或者悲观的人
can't see this as well?
就看不到好的一面呢?
Now to understand this,part of - this mic is great.
要明白这点…这个麦克风真好用
Thank you.Yes.
谢谢
I also agree it's a brilliant,a brilliant idea.
我也觉得这个一个好方法
\fe1\fnCalibri\fs15\b1\bord2\shad0\fsp0\c&H0ffffff&So part of what we are seeing here is we need to -
除了这些以外 我们还要…
in order to understand this,
为了要明白这个问题
let's talk a little bit about social rule breaking.
我们要讲一下打破社会规则
I believe that there are unscripted social rules that
我相信我们有一些不成文的社会规则
guide our life all the time that we never really talk about.
不停地指导着我们的生活 但我们不会讨论它们
I taught for social psychology.
我教过社会心理学
And for social psychology we,
在教社会心理学时
one of the things that we did for the class is that
我们在班上做过一件事
we split people up in pairs,
我们把同学分成两人一组
and made them go out and break social rules.
叫他们去打破社会规则
So they would go out during the week
在那一周里 他们会做很多事
and they would go into an elevator in one of the houses
他们会走进哈佛其中一间宿舍的电梯里
and then just slowly turned around in that elevator
然后慢慢地在电梯里转过身
and faced the people behind you.
面朝着身后的同学
Or just lie down in the elevator
或者在电梯里躺下来
and see if people will say anything,
看看那些同学会不会说什么
or go to Starbucks and haggle for the price of a coffee,
或者去星巴克 买杯咖啡时跟人讨价还价
saying you can get it cheaper if you made it at home.
说你在家里做的话要便宜很多
Or going to the Coop,
或者上Coop网站
attempting the barter system for one of the books.
用一本书来买东西
Or going to places and asking for free samples for things
或者去商店里问人要免费样品
that we can't get free sample for,like a Felipe's burrito.
那些没有免费样品的商品 例如Felipe's店的玉米煎饼
Or I know one guy who went into his athletic locker
我还知道有个同学走进他的运动员更衣室里
and then went up to everyone who is there and asked them
问遍更衣室里的每个人 问他们
if they would please soap up his back because he was tired.
愿不愿意帮他擦背 因为他太累了
Another girl would only take showers in the girls' locker room
还有一个女同学 在女生更衣室里
where somebody else was already taking a shower
看到有人在浴室里洗澡
where shower has already been used.
她就只进那个浴室洗澡
Another person C I mean you can do a lot of different things
还有一个同学…我想说明的是 有很多事情可以打破社会规则
like you can go into the bathroom
例如走进浴室
and strike up a conversation through the bathroom's door.
隔着浴室门和别人聊起来
This one is great.
这个非常好玩
You should do that here,say "hello,neighbor!"
你们应该试试看 "你好 隔壁的同学"
Talk amongst yourselves.
然后两个人聊起来
You know the funniest joke that - wow! Really magnified.
最好笑的笑话…声音真的变大了
Can you guys hear me?
你们能听到我吗?
Aww,this is great! This should happen all the time.
太棒了 早就该这样了
I got a lot of things back here now.
现在我后面有很多东西了
Where was I? This is not probably the talk.
我讲到哪里了?课堂上可能不应该说这种话
You guys know C I can never remember any jokes
你们知道…我记不住笑话的
but the funniest joke that they did on the website,
有人在网站上评选出一个最好笑的笑话
like they actually found out what the scientific funniest joke
他们看了网站上的笑话 真的找出了有科学根据的
was by doing reading on the website.
最好笑的笑话
And one of the Americans was a guy who is hunting -
有一个美国人去打猎
I can't tell jokes.
我不会讲笑话
But he was,
他…
this guy calls into a operator and goes,"operator! Operator!"
这个人找电话给接线员 他说"接线员"
This is 911.He says C this is why I can't tell jokes.
接线员说"这是911报警中心" 所以说我不会讲笑话
He was in Scranton,Pennsylvania.This is Tuesday.
他当时在宾夕法尼亚州的Scranton市 那天是星期二
Anyway,so he calls the operator and says,"Operator! Operator!
总之 他打电话给接线员说"接线员
I think I just shot my friend while we are hunting.
我刚才打猎时 我好像打中我的朋友了
I think he's dead!"
他好像死了"
And the operator goes,"OK.Calm down sir.Calm down sir.
接线员说"好的 冷静 先生
The very first thing that we need you to do
我们要你做的第一件事是
is check to make sure that he's dead."
确保你的朋友已经死了"
So he said,"OK.OK."
他说"好的"
And you hear this quiet,this pause,as he puts down the phone
经过一阵平静的停顿后 他放下电话
and a few seconds later you here gun shot.
几秒钟后听到枪声
PPPCCCHHHUUUUU!
砰!
And he comes back to his phone and says,"OK.He's dead.Now what?"
他拿起电话说"好的 现在他死了 接下来怎么办?"
This is the funniest joke in America.That's surprising.
这是美国最好笑的笑话 有点意外
The funniest joke in Europe was C not appropriate.
欧洲最好笑的笑话是…有点不适合在课堂上讲
It's: there's two ferrets sitting in a bar.
有两只雪貂坐在一间酒吧里
And one ferret says to the other ferret that,
一只雪貂中另一只说
"I slept with your mom last night."
"我昨晚和你妈妈睡了"
And the other ferret doesn't say anything.
另一个雪貂什么都没说
And the other ferret thinks that he doesn't say anything so he says
那只雪貂见它什么都没说 就说
"I slept with your mom last night."
"我昨晚和你妈妈睡了"
And the second ferret says nothing.
第二只雪貂还是什么都没说
And he finally -
最后它…
other ferret,ferret A said,"I slept with your mom last night."
另一个雪貂 雪貂A说"我昨晚和你妈睡了"
And ferret B says,"Dad,go home.You are drunk."
雪貂B说"爸爸 回家吧 你醉了"
[Laugh and applause]
掌声
So the interesting thing about this breaking of social rules
打破社会规则的一个有趣之处是
is not just the effect that it had on other people,
它不仅影响了其他人
or the awareness that we have,
影响了我们对于整天
social scripts that are surrounding us all the time.
围在我们身边的社会条文的意识
It's the awareness of how we act
当我们打破社会规则时
when we are breaking a social rule.
还使我们意识到了自己的行为
Some of the people that
有些同学
are attempting to do this experiment absolutely broke down.
做这个实验时大笑不止
They could not go on with this experiment.
他们连实验都做不下去了
Other people found humor in the awkwardness.
有些人在尴尬中发现幽默
And because of that,they were able to enjoy the experience
因此 他们能够享受这个实验
and actually cause other people more suffering.
把自己的快乐建筑在别人的痛苦之上
Part of what we are seeing here is that -
我们从中发现
absolutely is the mindset that
我们有一个心态
dictates whether or not something is going to be funny.
决定什么是好笑的 什么是不好笑的
And if it's mindset,it's within our control.
如果这真的是由心态决定 那我们就可以控制它
And today we are going to talk about some of the ways
今天我们就讲几个
you can actually control that.
控制这个心态的方法
But one of the things that we talked about earlier
我们这个学期之前讲过
in this semester was Wiseman's study on the luck factor.
Wiseman对幸运配方的研究
Remember the luck factor was
大家回忆一下 幸运配方是指
where he studied and actually created the luck school,
他研究 并创立了一间运气学校
in which you can teach people how to feel more lucky,
教人们怎么去觉得自己更幸运
and how you can give people the same exact scenario
给人们同一个情景
where some people would feel lucky,
有些人会觉得幸运
or some people would feel unlucky.
有些人会觉得不幸
So for example,if you walk into a bank,
例如 如果你走进一间银行
and you are there with a hundred people -
那里有100个人在等
actually let's say that we are here in -
假设 我们在…
we are not in Annenberg - we are here in Sanders.
我们不在Annenberg 我们在Sanders
And somebody walks in with a gun
有人拿着一支枪走进来
and fires his weapon one time and shoots me right in the arm.
开了一次枪 打中了我的手臂
Do I consider this to be a lucky event or an unlucky event?
这是走运还是倒霉?
Well according to Wiseman,
根据Wiseman所说
that depends upon the counterfactual I used to determine this.
这取决于我用什么反事实去看待这件事了
If I compare to every other time
如果我拿这件事跟
that I have been here and in the theater,
我平时进戏院的情况相比
that seems to be a pretty unlucky event,right?
那这件事肯定是倒霉了 对吧?
And it seems to be pretty unfortunate.
这样看 非常不幸
I mean there's a lot of other people in the room
这个房间里还有很多人
that this person can shoot.
这个人可以打中很多人
I went to the Divinity School.
我还是读过神学院的
I'm sure I'm better than at least one of the other people in here
我肯定比这个房间里至少一个人要好
and deserve this less.
肯定至少有一个人比我更活该中枪
So why was I the one that got shot?
可为什么偏偏打中我?
On the other hand,
但从另一方面看
the counter fact that I could use to compare to see
我可以用另一个反事实去跟这件事比较
if this is actually a lucky or not lucky event,that
看看这件事是走运还是倒霉
counter fact could be "well he could have shot me in the head."
这个反事实可以是"他有可能打中我的头"
Now I know I love that the optimistic
我喜欢这个乐观
and lucky view point as I always choose things
幸运的观点 因为我总是选择
that cause the most carnage and blood,right?
能造成最多伤害和流血的反事实 对吧?
Or I could've got shot in the head and the heart
或者说 我有可能被打中头部和心脏
and died upon stage bleeding to death.
流血过多而死
That would be - I'm definitely killing the mood.
这样…我坏了大家的心情了
This is just like every day.
每天都这样子
So it usually happens about 20 minutes in.
通常都是上课20分钟就这样
So based upon the way that I actually decide to counter a fact
所以这取决于我用什么反事实
to that determine whether or not I find something be funny.
来决定我觉得什么好笑 什么不好笑
In the same way,humor is the same way.
幽默也是同样道理
Look at how much the context matters.
环境非常重要
If I said something this fact,
如果我说一个事实
this innocuous like,"I cut my toe nail."
一件毫无感情的事 如"我弄断趾甲了"
That's not really funny.
这一点都不好笑
But if I said "I cut my toe nail in the class".
但如果我说"我在上课时弄断了趾甲"
Suddenly it seems to be like a little bit more funny.
这样说就有点好笑了
Not Haha funny but a little bit funnier.
不是很好笑 但有点好笑了
Or "alcohol makes you drunk" is an innocuous fact.
"酒精能使人醉" 这是一个毫无感情的事实
"Alcohol makes you drunk"
"酒精能使人醉"
before giving a lecture on humor is a little bit funnier.
在上一节讲幽默的课前说这句话就有点好笑了
So part of what we are seeing here is that
所以我们可以从中看出
the way that you view the environment,
你看待环境的视角
the way that you parse the world actually has a direct effect
你分析世界的视角 能直接影响
upon whether or not you find something to be funny
当你一听到某件事时 会不会觉得它
in the first place.
好笑
This is something we call in my sections
在我的课堂上 我们有两样东西叫
the Alpha press and the Beta press.
α因素和β因素
The Alpha press is the objective constraints of reality.
α因素就是指客观的现实约束
We are all experiencing the same Alpha press.
我们都有同样的α因素
We are all sitting in the same room with the same lights.
我们都坐在同一个教室 有同样的灯光
But our Beta press -
但我们的β因素
our subjective construal of reality,is different.
是对现实的主观感受 是不同的
Every person in here is experiencing something different -
这间教室里每个人都有不同的
they are experiencing -
感受
you are either like bored or tired or hungry right now.
有些人觉得无聊 有些觉得饿
Or excited and happy.I'm apparently nervous.
有些人觉得兴奋 有些觉得高兴 我觉得很紧张
And part of what you are seeing is that
我们从中看出
their way of viewing the world
他们看待世界的视角
absolutely has an effect upon how you view that Alpha press.
绝对会影响你如何看待α因素
Things we've been talking about positive psychology so far C
到目前为止 我们讲过的幸福心理学的内容…
I've been talking about the ways
我讲过在什么情况下
in which our Beta press is actually malleable -
我们的β因素是可塑的
that we can change our Beta press,
我们可以改变我们的β因素
and as a result have an extreme amount of changes
因此能大大地改变
in our adaptive behavior.
我们的适应行为
I think that humor is one of the most powerful ways
我认为幽默是一个很强大的工具
that we can actually change the Beta press by changing the way that
我们可以利用它通过改变我们看待环境的视角
we actually view our environment so it's actually adaptive for us
来改变我们的β因素 让它适应我们
There are something that they found at Harvard medical school
在哈佛医学院有一个
called the Tetris Effect.
俄罗斯方块效应
The Tetris Effect is - how many people play Tetris?
俄罗斯方块效应是…多少同学玩过俄罗斯方块?
A lot.Oooh! Yes.Oooh.
很多
Tetris is a C if you haven't played it C
俄罗斯方块是…还没玩过的同学
is a game in which shapes of different sizes
在这个游戏里 有不同大小的形状
fall from the ceiling as they do it in life.
从上面掉下来
And you rotate them around
你旋转这些形状
and you try and make straight lines across.
把这些形状排成一整排
And if you make a straight line all the way across,
如果一排排满了
the line disappears.
这一排就会消失
And you try to keep the shape going all the way up to the top.
然后你继续这样一直排到顶
What they found in their testing -
他们在试验中发现…
they are actually testing video games on college students.
他们找大学生来玩电子游戏
At the medical school,they found that
在医学院 他们发现
after students played about 4,5 hours of Tetris straight
学生连续玩了四五个小时的俄罗斯方块后
and get paid for,which is a pretty good deal.
他们是有钱拿的 非常好的一个交易
Then afterwards,they went back to their rooms
玩了以后 他们回到宿舍
and went on with their lives for the most part.
继续他们平常的生活
And there are subjective reports that some of these individuals
有主观报告说 这些学生
when they go into a super market,
当他们去到超市时
and start rearranging the bread on the shelf
他们开始重新排列货架上的面包
so they made straight lines.
让它们排成直直的一排
Or they'd be looking at the traffic and say,
或者他们看到路上的车时 会想
"Oh,I'll shape car here to complete that line
"我要把这辆车放到这里排在一排
and make friends that way."
这样来交朋友"
Or they would.Or this one guy was actually
或者他们会…有一个男同学
looking at the Sports Illustrated Swimsuit Calendar Issue
看着体育画报的泳装写真日历号
and when they had all the,
上面有
like a lot of models all together at one.
很多模特在同一张日历上
And his comment was - "I wish I had a Z shape woman
他说了一句话 "我希望有一个摆Z姿势的女人
who would fit and make that line all the way across."
她能放进这里 把这一排排满"
Clearly what he was doing was parsing the entire world
很明显他把整个世界都看成…
even a swimsuit calendar into whether or not
甚至包括一张泳装写真日历
he could change shapes in order to make straight lines.
他都看成能够改变形状 排出直直的一排
Every input has the brainwaves receiving.
每个输入的信息都有脑波接收
And our brains receive too much input all the time
我们的大脑接收了太多的信息
was being parsed through this one code.
大脑就形成了这个模式
Now what we find is that this is something
我们从中发现了一样东西
that I call a cognitive afterimage.
我称之为认知残象
A cognitive afterimage is just...
认知残象就是
If you stare the sun for a really long time,you are stupid.
如果你盯着太阳看一段时间 笨人做笨事
And what happens is you momentarily burn your retina.
结果就是你暂时性地烧伤了你的视网膜
And you can see this blue or green dot in your vision
你看东西时 就会看到一个蓝色或绿色的点
that goes around-
你看到哪里 它就跟到哪里
happens when a lot of flash photography goes off
我在Kirkland宿舍看到太多照相机闪光灯
when I'm at Kirkland House.
就会出现这种情况
There are a lot of times after when this can occur.
出现这种情况后 很多时候都会这样子
So what that is is the afterimage on your retina.
你的视网膜有一个残象
Well the same thing happens on the cognitive level as well.
在认知层面上也有同样的现象
Our brains can actually retain an afterimage and in Tetris effect
我们的大脑能保存一个残象 在俄罗斯方块效应里
what was happening is the cognitive afterimage,
学生会有一个认知残象
that people were getting stuck with,was viewing the world
这个残象会停留 他们看这个世界时
through the lens of parsing the world into ways
就会把世界上的事物看成
that can rotate shapes to make straight lines.
能够旋转变形 排进一条直线里
So too the individuals who are doing humor.
幽默的人也是这样
The people that can look at something like
当人们看到某件事…
writers for Jon Stewart,or the writers for Steven Colbert Report
例如Jon Stewart的编剧 或者"Steven Colbert报告"的编剧
When they look at the newspaper,
当他们看报纸时
when they see something that seems to be neutral
当他们看到一件不悲不喜的事
or even sad or tragic,they start to change the shape.
或者一件悲剧时 他们就开始让它变形
They rotate the shape in their mind.
他们在脑海里把这件事旋转变形
As a result,they are looking for patterns all the time.
结果他们就会不停地寻找模式
They are looking for multiple potentials within a status quo;
他们能从一件事上找到无限可能性
instead of just seeing a newspaper,
而不是只看到一张报纸
they see the possibility of humor that can come out of that.
他们能从报纸上看到幽默
And as you can find,
你们能发现
you can find that this can be a detriment sometimes as well.
认知残象有时也会带来坏处
You can get stuck in pattern
你会在一个思维模式中出不来
of looking for things that are humorous,
总是找幽默的东西
which can be adaptive or if you are in a fight,
这样有时会有利于适应 但如果你是和人吵架
and all you can do is making jokes - can be very mal-adaptive.
你唯一能做的就是开玩笑 这是非常不利于适应的
So one last thing about humor as a transformative lens
所以把幽默作为改变我们视角的东西还有一件事要注意的
before we talk about the benefits of humor is that
在我们讲幽默的益处前 我们先来讲一个这个
when we laugh at something,
当我们笑某件事时
Peter Berger argues that we get a momentary,
Peter Berger认为 我们会暂时性地
a momentary suspension of reality -
暂时地中止了现实
that when we can see something that is alternative to reality,
我们能看到一些有别于现实的东西
it teaches us that the status quo,
它让我们知道
the reality that we are seeing in front of us is both malleable
我们眼前的现实 是可塑的
and is not the only possible reality,
它不是唯一一种可能的现实
that the status quo absolutely can be changed.
现状是可以改变的
So humor provides a way of being actually more mindful.
所以幽默可以使我们变得更正念
Ellen Langer defines mindfulness
Ellen Langer把正念定义为
as "being present in the situation",
"留心眼前的情景"
so that you can be aware of the potentials in that environment.
这样你就能留意到环境中的可能性
The definition that I give for humor is almost word for word
我给幽默下的定义和正念的定义
of what you see with mindfulness.
几乎一模一样
The reason is that I think
原因是 我认为
when you are really present in the situation
当你真的留心眼前的情景
and when you view the world through a specific pattern,
当你以某种模式来看待世界时
what you are doing is you are actually parsing the world in a way
你实际上就是在用一种方式分析世界
that actually shows more potentials than that environment.
这种方式使得你能看到比环境本身更多的可能性
So Maslow argues that we have these peak experiences
所以Maslow认为我们会有高峰体验
where for momentarily we put on the cloak of self-actualization.
这时我们会暂时地披上了自我实现的披风
When we put this cloak of self-actualization,
当我们披上这件自我实现的披风时
we momentarily gain and see
我们就能暂时地获得和看到
and glimpse the potentials we actually have.
我们实际拥有的潜力
So too I think the humor is in the same vein.
所以我认为幽默也是这样
I think we momentarily take on self-actualization,
我认为我们暂时地假装达成了自我实现
because while we are provided with the reality,
因为当我们假装有这个现实时
in which the consequences for actions
在这个现实里 行为后果
don't have a negative effect upon us,
不会对我们产生负面影响
where we see life giving reality and happiness,
我们会看到人生的真实和幸福
even in the situation that seems dry and sad to other people.
即使是我们处于一个别人觉得枯燥悲伤的境地
The ordinary becomes extraordinary,
平凡就变得非凡
which is one of the traits of peak experiences
这是Abraham Maslow所说的高峰体验的
as Abraham Maslow did.
一个特征
I think the Office is a great example of this.
我觉得"办公室"就是一个很好的例子
I have two one minute clips from the Office
我有两段"办公室"的一分钟视频
that I want to show you,
我想放给你们看
of where they are taking something that's just -
在这个片段里 他们可以把一些…
you are in an office,doing something that is ordinary
在办公室里的工作是很平凡的
and take the ordinary and make it extraordinary.
他们能把平凡的变为非凡的
How many people are there watch the Office?
班上有多少同学看"办公室"?
How many people are there not watch the Office? Wow.
有多少同学不看?
How many people are not funny?
有多少同学是不幽默的?
Some of you are not raising your hands -I know that's not true.
有些人没举手 我知道不止这么少
OK.So,good.
好的
How many people in here think they are above,
有多少同学认为自己的幽默感
having them above the average sense of humor? Raise your hand.
是在中上水平的?举起手来
How many people
有多少同学
think they are a below average sense of the humor?
认为自己的幽默感是中下水平的?
By the way this would be the rest of you.
刚才没举手的那些都是了
I don't know what other option you've been waiting for.
我不知道你们还想我举出什么水平来让你们选
How many people think you are exactly average?
有多少人认为自己正好处于中等水平的?
The funny people.All right.
幽默的同学 好的
So let's watch these two clips
我们来看这两段视频
and we'll watch how the ordinary becomes extraordinary.
来看看如何把平凡变为非凡
[CLIP: THE OFFICE Season 3 - Episode 15 "Phyllis' Wedding"]
片段：办公室 第三季 15集
Jim: Damn,lost another file.Going to have to reboot.Again.
糟了 又丢了一个文件 又要重启了
Hey,Dwight,do you want an Altoid?
Dwight 你想吃薄荷糖吗?
Dwight: What do you think?
你说呢?
Jim: In school,we learned about this scientist
上学时 我们学过一个故事 说有个科学家
who trained dogs to salivate at the sound of a bell
训练狗一听到铃声就流口水
by feeding them whenever a bell rang.
方法就是每次响铃时都给东西它们吃
For the last couple of weeks
过去几周
I've been conducting a similar experiment.
我在做一个类似的实验
Jim: Dwight,want an Altoid?
Dwight 想吃薄荷糖吗?
Dwight: Okay.
好的
Jim: Altoid?
吃薄荷糖吗?
Dwight: Sure.
好的
Jim: Mint,Dwight?
要薄荷糖吗 Dwight?
Dwight: Inbwit? Yes.
Inbwit的吗?好的
Jim: What are you doing?
你在干什么?
Dwight: I...
我…
Jim: What?
什么?
Dwight: I don't know.My mouth tastes so bad all of a sudden.
我不知道 我突然嘴巴很臭
Shawn Achor:There is one more.
还有一个
[CLIP: THE OFFICE C Season 2 Episode 21 Conflict Resolution]
片段：办公室 第二季 21集
Michael: So Dwight,in your own words -
Dwight 你说
"Someone replaced all my pens and pencils with crayons,
"有人用蜡笔换走了我所有的钢笔和铅笔
I suspect Jim Halpert.
我怀疑是Jim Halpert
Everyone has called me Dwanye all day.
所有人都叫了我一整天的Dwanye
I think Jim Halpert paid them to."
我觉得是Jim Halpert给钱他们 叫他们这么做的"
Jim: YES! 5 bucks each,and it was totally worth it.
是的 每个五美元 花得很值
Michael: "By the end of the day,
"到下班时
my desk was about two feet closer to the copier."
我的办公桌离复印机近了两英尺"
Jim: Yeah,
是的
I just moved it an inch every time he went to the bathroom.
每次他上洗手间 我就移动一英寸
And that's how I spent my entire day that day.
我那天一整天只干了这件事
Michael: "Every time I typed my name it said 'diapers'."
"每次我输入我的名字 都会变成'尿布'"
Jim: Just a simple macro.
用一个简单的宏就行了
Michael: "This morning,
"今天早上
I knocked myself in the head with the phone."
我拿电话时 撞到了自己的头"
Jim: That actually took awhile.
这个花了我不少时间
I had to put more and more nickels into his handset,
我要一次放一个硬币进他的电话听筒
til he got used to the weight,
等他习惯了那个重量以后
and then I just ... took them all out.
我就把全部硬币都拿出来
Shawn:So just as Jim performs some of his experiments on Dwight,
Jim用Dwight来做这些实验
so too these experiments are gonna reveal
这些实验也告诉了我们
how much humor actually has a positive effect upon us.
幽默对我们有多大的积极影响
Not only when we are watching the Office,
我们不但会看"办公室"
but when we ourselves choose to surround ourselves with people
我们还会选择与幽默的人为伴
that are funny or decide to be funny ourselves.
或者让自己变得幽默
In order to understand this,there are two parts of human body.
为了弄明白这点 我要讲两个身体部位
Write that down.Only two parts.
写下来 只有两个
The sympathetic nervous system
交感神经系统
and the parasympathetic nervous system.
和副交感神经系统
P-A-R-A: the parasympathetic nervous system.
副字拼作para 副交感神经系统
The sympathetic nervous system is the part of the body
交感神经系统是我们身体里
that's responsible for dropping chemicals into your body
一个负责释放化学物质进我们身体里
that prepare you for fight or flight.
让你准备作出或战或逃反应的系统
It momentarily makes you super human.
它能暂时地让你当一回超人
You are stronger; you are faster;
你变强了 你变快了
you have more endurance; you have more energy.
你忍耐力变强了 你更有活力了
Now the problem with being super human all the time
但问题是 一直当这样的超人的话
and I should know is that it's catabolic,
是有分解代谢作用的
is that when you dump these chemicals into your body
当你把这些化学物释放到你的身体时
while your body becomes stronger momentarily,
虽然你的身体暂时变强壮了
it actually is tearing down every single organ in your body.
但其实它在损害你身体里的所有器官
Stress has its effect where it actually wears out every tissue,
压力是有影响的 它会劳损所有组织
living tissue in your body.
你体内的活组织
Now that's not the end of the story fortunately,
幸好 不是只有这么一个系统
because we don't just get more and more excited -
因为我们不会变得越来越兴奋
our heart rate keeps increasing until we just explode.
我们的心跳不会一直飙升 直到心脏爆炸
Because we have the other part of our central nervous system,
因为我们中枢神经系统里还有另一部分
called the parasympathetic nervous system.
叫做副交感神经系统
The parasympathetic nervous system
副交感神经系统
is responsible for calming the body down,
负责让我们的身体冷静下来
for slowing our breath rate,for slowing our heart rate.
它负责减慢我们的呼吸率 心跳率
It's the part that actually causes rejuvenation.
真正让我们恢复过来的就是它
And while we don't feel the spike in our energy levels,
当我们能量水平没有飙升时
we have a longer sustained period of energy,
我们的能量就能维持更长时间
because we are constantly revitalizing,
因为这个系统会不断地激活
repairing,and creating more energy in and of itself.
修复 并注入更多的活力
Helpful drawing.
很有帮助的图表
So what does this call is a -
这个称之为…
somebody calls it the Soprano Effect.
有人称之为黑道家族效应
I call it the Soprano Effect - no one else calls that.
其实只有我称之为黑道家族效应
But we'll test on it anyway.
但我们还是会考
So the Soprano Effect
黑道家族效应
is the chronic activation of the sympathetic nervous system.
是指长期地激活交感神经系统
And this is what a lot of Harvard students,including myself do,
很多哈佛学生 包括我自己都会这么做
is that when we are about go prepare for a test
我们准备为考试复习时
or dealing with anything in our lives,
或者处理生活中某些事情时
I hear so many people before the test say,
我听到很多人在考试前会说
"I'm totally gonna fail this test.
"这次考试我一定不会及格了
I'm not ready for this test at all.
我压根就没准备好
I'm totally gonna fail this test."
我一定会不及格了"
Or they say themselves,
或者他们心里想
"Oh,I'm so busy.I'm so busy.I'm so stressed."
"我太忙了 我压力太大了"
And when they do that,
当他们这么想时
what they are doing is we are leaving everything for last minute,
他们其实是把事情都留到最后一刻才做
like Tal was talking about procrastination.
就像Tal说的拖延症
The resulting effect is that
结果是
you get that momentary burst of energy,
你的能量会短暂地飙升
because your sympathetic nervous system is activating.
因为你的交感神经系统被激活了
So we get used to that.
所以我们习惯了这么做
We get addicted to using that
我们会上瘾地用
sympathetic nervous system for that boost.
交感神经系统刺激我们的能量
And we think that
我们认为
energy was actually gonna allow us to accomplish things.
能量可能让我们完成工作
Tony Soprano is in a non-reality but on the HBO series,
Tony Soprano不是现实人物 是HBO剧集里的
is a mob boss.
黑帮老大
And he - the part of the point of the series is that
这个电视剧的一个主旨就是
he had to go to therapy which is not necessarily
他要去接受心理治疗
something you want to do as a nefarious crime boss.
对于一个恶贯满盈的黑帮老大 没必要这样做
And he had to go to therapy because he was having panic attacks.
他要去看心理医生 因为他惊恐症发作
His body was shutting down,because he was responding to the fact
他的身体停止运作 因为他长期激活
that he was constantly activating his sympathetic nervous system,
他的交感神经系统 所以就发作了
whether be his nefarious actions as a crime lord boss -
不管是他当黑帮老大时做种种犯法的事
crime lord bo...
黑帮老大
Whatever C crime lord boss and a couple of adjectives.
黑帮老大 前面加一连串的形容词
Or living with his family,
还是平常和他家人的生活
trying to live a normal life,living in New Jersey which -
过一个正常的生活 他住在新泽西
living in New Jersey will be even more stressful.
住在新泽西的压力就更大了
And as a result of this,his body was just shutting down.
因此 他的身体停止运作
And,so part of what was happening -
所以原因之一就是
he was chronically activating his sympathetic nervous system.
他长期激活他的交感神经系统
So the same thing that happens with Harvard students
哈佛的学生也是这样
is that often times when we would decide to use that activation,
经常我们都会利用这种激活
that chronic activation of our sympathetic nervous system
我们会长期激活我们的交感神经系统
and as a result we wear down our bodies.
因此我们就会耗损我们的身体
And our bodies actually begin to shut down.
我们的身体就会开始停止运作
Fortunately that's not the end of the story.
幸好 我们还有救星
The greatest buffer against the Soprano Effect is humor.
对抗黑道家族效应的最佳缓冲剂是幽默
And the reason is that humor,
原因是 幽默
just like mindfulness and meditation,
就像正念和冥想
activate the parasympathetic nervous system.
它能激活副交感神经系统
And as a result of that,several extraordinary things happen.
因此 非凡的事就发生了
It's amazing that
很让人惊讶的是
laughter, something we consider to be just a luxury,
我们觉得大笑是一件奢侈的事
something that we do just in our free time
我们有时间的时候才会大笑
as if we have nothing else to do
我们没事可做时才会大笑
has such a dramatic effect upon our lives.
但它对我们的生活却有如此巨大的影响
First of all,laughter itself is both medicine and exercise.
首先 笑本身既是一种药也是一种运动
If you like Jack Candy and deep thoughts from Saturday Night Live
如果你喜欢Jack Candy和"周六夜现场"的"深层思考"小品
there is some quote about - there is something like,
我引用几句话给大家听 其中有一句是
"as my father always said,the laughter is the best medicine.
"我爸爸总是说 笑是最好的药
That's probably why several of us died of tuberculosis,"
可能这就是为什么我们几个有家人死于肺结核"
which is not all that funny,but I decided to go for it anyway.
其实不是很好笑 但我还是决定说这句
And so it's also a form of exercise that every time you laugh,
笑也是一种运动 每次你笑
if you've chosen to laugh at some point during this lecture,
如果你想在这节课上笑
or if you are planning on laughing after the lecture,
或者你想下课后才笑
what happens is your body is actually doing a lot of exercise.
你笑时 你的身体就在做大量运动
I already told you
我已经说过
how many muscles you actually contract in your body.
你笑时 身体有多少块肌肉在伸缩
Well it turns out just 10 to 15 minutes of laughing,
我们发现 只要笑10到15分钟
10 to 15 minutes of laughing actually
笑10到15分钟
is enough to burn the amount of calories
所消耗的卡路里
of a medium size block of chocolate,which is pretty good.
就相等于一块中等大小的巧克力 非常棒
Also some people report just minute of laughing
有些人的报告说 只要笑几分钟
is enough to get their heart rate up
就足够让他们的心率飙升到
more than 15 minutes of rowing machine exercise.
比在划式练力机上做15分钟运动还要高
It depends on what you actually are rowing at the time.
这就要看你划的是什么了
They also find that it causes - this is amazing,amazing that
他们还发现它能导致…非常厉害的是
humor will do something like this at the chemical level -
幽默还能够在化学层面上起作用
that it actually increases our T-cells in our body
它能增加我们体内的T细胞
which actually strengthen our immune system;
从而加强我们的免疫系统
increasing our Gamma-interferon,
增加我们的γ-干扰素
which is the disease fighting protein
它是一种抵抗疾病的蛋白质
as well as increasing our B-cells
还会增加我们的B细胞
which are responsible for creating antibodies
B细胞负责生成抗体
to actually prepare our body to defend against disease.
加强我们身体抵抗疾病的能力
The humor is actually making us better defended against reality,
所以幽默真的能帮我们更好地对抗现实
right?
对吧
It's actually preparing our body to defend itself
它真的能加强我们的身体 帮助我们
against the outside world.
对抗外部世界
It's partly the way that it exists,
这就是幽默的作用之一
and part of the reason that affects the Soprano Effect
它能够影响黑道家族效应的原因之一
is that researchers like Sultanoff found that
就是像Sultanoff这样的研究人员发现的那样
laughter decreases the amount of serum cortisol
笑能降低我们体内的
that occurs in our body.
血清皮质醇
Cortisol is released when we have a stress response.
当我们感受到压力时 就会释放皮质醇
That stress response
应激反应…
if I cause you to be stressful for whatever reason,
如果我做了某些事 让你感到有压力了
and your cortisol levels begin to go up;
你的皮质醇水平就会上升
if you cause somebody to laugh midway during that experience,
如果你在这时候引人发笑
their cortisol levels actually decrease again;
他们的皮质醇水平就会降低
that if they are going through a stressful event,
也就是说在他们感受到压力时
laughing in the midst
大笑起来
and going through that event will actually allow them
在压力中笑起来 能够使他们
to not have all the negative effects of stress,
降低压力带来的消积影响
whichCrememberCtear down every organ in your body.
大家回忆一下 压力会耗损我的身体
In addition,there is a ton of mental and physical benefits
除此以外 幽默还能给我们的心理和生理
that accrue because of this.
累积大量的益处
First of all,they find that
首先 他们发现
even small doses of humor actually increase our immune system.
即使是一点点的幽默 就能提高我们的免疫系统
So what they did
他们的研究方法是
is they brought in people who had bronchial asthma.
他们找来一些患有支气管哮喘病的人
And they exposed them to the dust mite
让他们接触尘螨
which they are highly allergic to -
这些病人对尘螨是极度过敏的
just make sure that they had those responses.
这样是为了让他们产生过敏反应
Pretty sure that these were the same people
我很肯定这群研究人员就是
that did the ipecac pregnancy studies that
上次做那个吐根怀孕研究的那些人
we talked about earlier on in the course or the learned helpless-
我们在这门课上讲过那个研究 或者是那个
that's the one who kept shocking the dogs over and over again.
一次又一次地电击狗 习得无助感实验的那群研究员
So in this case for the bronchial asthma,
在这个支气管哮喘实验中
they exposed them to this dust mite which,umm,potentially fatal
他们让这些病人接触尘螨 有致命危险的
And then they had them go away for a little,
他们只让他们接触一点点
but they wanted to make sure that
但他们至少要保证数量要足以
everyone had an effect based upon this dust mite.
让所有病人都对尘螨产生过敏反应
Then they had the people come back to the experiment
然后他们找这些人回来做实验
which shows how smart these people are.
看来这些人是真的学不精的
And these people with bronchial asthma
这些患有支气管哮喘的病人
came back to the same experiment.
回来做同一个实验
And half of them before they were exposed to the dust mite again
有一半人在接触尘螨之前
were just told a joke C
先听一个笑话
I don't know what joke they were told but it had to be -
我不知道他们听了什么笑话
they had actually to laugh at it.
反正他们笑了
And the other group was a neutral group,
然后另一组是对照组
one that they just had to watch or listen to a neutral story.
他们只是看了或听了一个很普通的故事
And that shouldn't have any effect
这些故事不会减轻
upon the way a dust mite affects somebody with bronchial asthma.
支气管哮喘患者对尘螨的过敏反应
But what they found was that people that
他们发现
have been told a single joke to beforehand show statistically
数据上表明 那些先听过一个笑话的人
significantly smaller amounts of flare-up due,
哮喘病发作的数量
flare-up in terms of their asthma.
要少很多
I can't imagine -
我很难想象…
I was trying to think of funny jokes you could tell people.
我想说一个好笑的笑话 好让你们讲给别人听
I couldn't come up with anything.
但我想不出来
You probably will think of something better than this,
你们想的笑话可能都比我想的这个要好笑
but I think like.. No,actually I'm not gonna go for that.
但我想…算了 我不说这个笑话
Never mind.It wasn't funny.
不说了 不好笑的
I was going to do a knock-knock joke about bronchial asthma,
我本来想说一个关于哮喘病的"敲门"玩笑
but it isn't funny.
但我发现不好笑
So we also find humor also increases pain tolerance.
我们还发现 幽默还能提高忍痛度
So there's a group of German researchers C
有一群德国研究人员
of course they would be German researchers -
除了德国研究人员还会有谁
to find and put individuals,
他们找人来
the participants to sign up for this study,
找参与者来参加这个研究
put their hands in ice cold ice water.
把他们的手放在冰冷的冰水里
Now this is a standard way in psychology
这是心理学以及医学界中
and medical experience of testing somebody's pain tolerance.
测试一个人的忍痛度的标准做法
Because there's usually no lasting effect upon individuals
因为这个测试不会对人造成永久伤害
except for debilitating frost-bite.
只会加重他们的冻疮
So what they find is that
他们发现
they keep their hands in frozen bucket of ice water,
他们把手放进冰水桶里
and during this period -
在这期间
so the longer you keep it in,the better your pain tolerance is.
你的手放得越久 你的忍痛度就越高
Try with your friends.This is a great party trick.
你可以和朋友试试 这是一个很好的派对游戏
And one of the things you can do
你可以
is you can have one person watch a funny video,
让一个人看好笑的视频
one person watch a neutral video,
一个人看不悲不喜的视频
and one person watch sad video while they are doing this.
一个人看悲伤的视频 这时候他们的手都放在冰水里
And what they found was that the group
他们发现
that was watching the humor video
看幽默视频的那一组
could keep their hand in the ice bucket
在数据上来看
for statistically significantly longer than the other groups,
手放在冰桶里的时间要比其他组长很多
the other groups of people,
比其他组的人长很多
which means that if you find humor funny,
这意味着 如果你觉得幽默好笑
you are probably not as smart as other people
你可能没有别人聪明
and you can keep your hand in the ice bucket
但你能把手放在冰桶里
for longer periods of time.
更久
But this is amazing.This is amazing.
但这个研究还有一个惊人发现
It wasn't just during experiment that they had found this effect.
幽默的影响不仅现出在实验过程中
They even decided to test people 20 minutes
他们在这些人看完幽默视频后20分钟
after they were exposed to humor.
再对他们进行测试
20 minutes after they were exposed to humor -
看完幽默视频20分钟后
the same effect occurred that there was a 20 minute
还能有同样的效果 即使是看了幽默视频
after effect of watching something
20分钟后 幽默还能有一个后效应
that was humorous in terms of your pain tolerance.
提高你的忍痛度
Now this has a lot to do
这个结果
and a lot of implications thus for people
给了人们很多启示
that are experiencing chronic fatigue or chronic pain
那些日常生活中因为患有疾病
in their own lives due to diseases,
而有慢性疲劳 或者慢性痛的人
and the way which humor itself could play a role in that.
幽默可以减轻他们的疲劳或疼痛
They also found that after you eat a large meal,
他们还发现在你狂吃一顿后
that if you have type 2 diabetes and you eat a large meal,
如果你有II型糖尿病 而你狂吃了一顿
that if you are watching something
如果你吃完后
that's humorous afterwards as opposed to something that's neutral
看了一些好笑的东西 而不是一些平平淡淡的东西
surprisingly your blood sugar actually was much lower
令人惊讶地 你的血糖会
than the group that have eaten the same exactly meal,
比那些吃了同样多的人 低很多
which is amazing that it's occurring.
这种效果太惊人了
And finally they found it decreases stress
最后 他们还发现幽默能减少压力
and increases remission rates in terms of cancer.
增加癌症的缓解率
For example one of the studies was on testicular cancer.
例如 有一个关于睾丸癌的研究
And they found that these individuals
研究人员发现 患者
once they can find a way of laughing and coping,
如果能笑出来
using laughter as coping mechanism,the individual
能用笑作为他们的心理应付机制
that found laughter as a coping mechanism versus those
那些用笑来作为心理应会机制的患者
that did not showed increased levels of remission.
比起那些没有这样做的患者 他们的缓解有所提高
In fact their symptoms
甚至
that they are experiencing actually decrease.
他们的症状也减少了
And they had higher levels of pain tolerance and decreased stress
他们的忍痛度提高了
because of the infliction that they were feeling.
伴随这些病痛而来的压力也减少了
Now as a result of this,
因此
we've seen some pretty remarkable things about humor.
我们看到幽默真的有很多惊人的益处
I mean we've seen the ways in which it changes our body chemistry
我们看到它能改变我们的身体化学
it changes the way our immune system actually fights
改变我们的免疫系统
and defends against these things,
帮助我们对抗疾病
it changes our stress levels,
它改善我们的压力水平
it changes the way that our body responds to dust mite
改善我们身体对尘螨的反应
and to food and to testicular cancer.
对食物的反应 对癌症的反应
There are a lot of different ways that
幽默从方方面面
humor actually has an effect upon us,which is remarkable.
影响我们 效果非常惊人
But also I want to talk about the social effects of humor as well
我还想谈谈幽默的社会影响
Now if you are here on the very first day of class,
如果你是第一天来这里上学的
I told you these statistics.
我要跟你说几个数据
But I just want to remind you about these statistics,
我只是想提醒大家几个数据
that last year when we tested the Harvard students,
去年我们在哈佛学生中做了一个调查
we found that
我们发现
the average number of romantic relationships at Harvard
哈佛学生的谈恋爱的次数
was less than one.
少于一次
And the average number of sexual partners was between 0 and .5,
平均的性伴侣人数在0到0.5之间
the scientific equivalent of second base.
用科学数据给二垒定了量
And we also found that 24% of you are currently unaware
我们还发现你们当中有24%的同学不知道
if you are involved in a romantic relationship.
自己是不是在谈恋爱
Now I just remind you about this,
我想跟大家说这几个数据
because I think that this is one of the areas
是因为我觉得
where humor could actually do us a lot of good at Harvard.
幽默能给我们哈佛学生在恋情中带来很大帮助
So I taught for human sexuality at Harvard as well,
我还在哈佛教一门叫人类性欲的课
which is an awkward class.
那是一门很尴尬的课
How many people took human sexuality? Just one.
有多少同学上了人类性欲?只有一个
Hello.This is awkward.
你好 真尴尬
So one of the things,
其中…
the reason why it's so awkward is the very first paper that
我说它尴尬的原因是
the students had to write was ten page paper
学生要写的第一篇论文 是一篇十页的
on their first sexual encounter,
讲自己第一次性行为的论文
which I then had to grade.
我要评阅这些论文
That's really awkward.
非常尴尬
And I had to make comments like
我还要写评论
"no,there's no way that happened,"or
"不 不可能这样" 或者说
"this paper took a lot longer to write than you've ever had sex."
"写这篇论文的时间要比你做爱的时间长很多"
There's a lot of awkwardness that could possibly...
有很多尴尬的事
But one of the things
但是…
that was most awkward about this is that they,
最尴尬的一次是
for one of the sections
有一节课
they wanted us to show condoms to the Harvard students,
他们想我给哈佛学生看看安全套是什么样的
because well of the statistics that just showed chances
因为数据表明 你们哈佛学生很可能
are you haven't seen a condom or anything to rhyme sex.
连安全套或者其他与性有关的东西都没见过
And so what they found is that,
他们发现这个现象
they wanted us to give these condoms out in sections
他们想我在一节课上分发安全套
so everyone could see one.
这样大家都能拿一个看看
And so I was teaching four sections for this class
我那天要教四个班
so I stuffed 80 condoms into the front pouch of my backpack.
于是我把80个安全套塞进背包的前袋
And I was sitting at Starbucks,which is my coffice.
当时我坐在星巴克里 星巴克是我的咖啡店兼办公室
And I spent all day there,rented out a dollar 49 a day.
我整天都坐在那里 一天只需交1.49美元的租金
And I find that while I was sitting there -
我发现我坐在那里时
I don't why I keep saying that - "find".
我不知道我为什么很喜欢说"发现"
While I was sitting there,there is this girl sitting next to me.
我当时坐在那里 旁边坐了一个女孩
And at one point she turned to me and she said,
这时她转过身 跟我说
"Do you have a pen that I can borrow?"
"你能借支笔给我吗?"
And I said,"Oh,absolutely! I can definitely get you a pen!"
我说"当然能 当然能借支笔给你"
And then I was totally forgetting.
然后我完全忘了
And I opened up my backpack
我打开我的背包
and 80 condoms exploded all over her,
80只安全套夺包而出 掉到了她身上
all over her table,all over the floor underneath her.
她的桌子上 她脚下的地板上满是安全套
It took me like 4 minutes to pick all the condoms underneath her.
我花了四分钟才捡完她脚下的安全套
I offered her one.
我还递了一个给她
She didn't want that or my pen.
她不想要安全套 也不想要我的笔
But research that's done on first encounters like this
研究这种第一次相遇的研究
has been pretty remarkable.
得到非常惊人的发现
Fraley did some research
Fraley做了一些研究
where you bring people into - forgot something.
他会找一些人来…有个知识点忘了讲
We'll come back.
我们等一下再讲
Fraley found that if you bring people into a room,participants,
Fraley发现 如果你把实验参与者带到一个房间
and they are strangers,and you have them do cooperative task.
他们互不认识 你让他们做一个合作任务
You have them do a cooperative task.
你让他们做一个合作任务
One of TF love the attraction and bondage on my titles.
有个助教很喜欢我标题中的"吸引与感情"这两个词
I just think it's funny.So I totally lost my train of thoughts.
我觉得很好笑 我想不起要讲什么了
I'll talk about mirror neurons instead.
我讲另一个内容吧 镜像神经元
Mirror neurons are awesome.Cause I skipped this a minute ago.
镜像神经元非常厉害 因为我刚才忘了讲这个
Mirror neurons - we didn't even know we had it in brain,
镜像神经元 我们以前不知道大脑里有这个
in the human brain until about ten years ago,
直到十年前才知道
or actually about even less than that.
或能还不到十年
Then we began to become aware of them .
我们那时才发现它们的存在
But there's a part that if somebody smiles at you,
它们的作用就是 如果有人对你笑
you almost have to smile back at them.
通常你一定也会对他们笑
And the reason is because there's part of your brain
原因是 因为你大脑有个部位
is lighting up as you are smiling as well,
在你笑时 亮起来了
just as if I was standing on stage as somebody came over
就好像我站在讲台上 有个人走过来
and tackled me really hard,and everyone goes,"Ooh."
狠狠地把我绊倒 大家都会惊呼
You know like feeling mad C you are actually,
你们会觉得很愤怒
your brain is lighting up those mirror neurons are lighting up,
你们有大脑会亮起来 那些镜像神经元会亮起来
as if you just got tackled as well,
就好像你也被绊倒了一样
which is reason why people groan at football games
这也是为什么人们看橄榄球比赛时会发生痛苦的叫声
even if they are 2000 miles away from the actual stadium.
即使他们离体育场有2000英里远
We are actually literally hardwired for empathy for other people.
我们天生会对别人有移情作用
As a result of that,humor is extremely contagious,
因此 幽默非常具有传染性
because these mirror neurons begin to activate
因为当我们看到别人笑时
when we see other people laughing.
我们的镜像神经元就会激活
Now the reason why this is helpful is because of the attraction
幽默之所以能帮助我们的社交 是因为
that it causes in these first situations.
第一次相遇时 它能制造吸引力
So what they found is they bring in strangers,
他们发现 他们找来互不认识的参与者
have them play a competitive game.
让他们玩一个竞赛游戏
Afterwards you have them rank the attractiveness and
之后让他们评价对方的吸引力
how closely they feel bonded to the person they are working with.
以及他们对比赛对手产生了多少感情
And usually the levels of attraction and bondage were pretty low.
通常他们的吸引力和感情都很低
For the middle group,
中间那组
you have somebody come in and you have them do a cooperative task
你找人来合作完成一个任务
This is similar to the Wall Street and community games studies
跟Tal这个学期讲过的
that Tal was talking about earlier on this semester.
华尔街和社区运动会的研究很相似
And this experiment - when you have a cooperative task,
在这个实验里 如果是合作完成任务
people's attractiveness,the ratings of attraction
参与者的吸引力 两个人的吸引力
and bondage for both of the individuals go up.
和感情都上升了
But if you have that individual do
但如果你让参与者做
an extremely awkward task together,like play Twister,
一件很尴尬的事 例如玩扭扭乐
or you have somebody come into the room
或者让人走进房间
that this experimenters are in,
实验参与者所在的房间
and ask them accidently pour water on one of the participants,
叫他们不小心地把水倒到其中一个参与者身上
telling them that they are awkward and leaving the room,
告诉他们 他们笨手笨脚的 然后离开房间
allowing them to laugh about it,those individuals -
让他们笑这件事 这些人…
because there is something humorous that is going on -
因为这个过程中发生了幽默的事
showed the highest ratings of other persons being attractive,
所以给对方评的吸引力分数是最高的
and showed the highest levels of bondage.
而且感情也是最深的
Now what this means is next time you are sitting at a bar,
所以 下次如果你坐在酒吧里
you shouldn't attempt to do some sort of a competitive
你不要试图去跟那个人比个高低
or a cooperative task with that individual,
或者跟那个人合作
you should either suggest to play Twister
你可以请他们玩扭扭乐
or pour your drink on them and tell them how awkward they are.
或者把酒倒在他们身上 告诉他们 他们有多笨手笨脚
That witty repertoire
这个诡计
is definitely going to increase your bondage.
一定能增加你们的感情
So what they find is dating is an interesting case
他们发现在研究幽默这个课题时
when it comes to humor,
约会是一个很有趣的研究对象
especially in terms of the social elements.
尤其是研究它的社会因素
So we know that there are certain things that
我们知道人们是会
people are attracted to in the physical domain,
被某些身体特征吸引的
but there should be no evolutionary advantage at all C right? C
但为什么有些人会选择幽默的人
to why somebody would pick somebody who is humorous,right? Yeah.
幽默应该不是一种进化优势 对吧?
How many people in the room would not date somebody
这班上有多少同学是不会
if they didn't make enough money?
和赚不了多少钱的人约会的?
Just raise your hand.OK.
举起手来 好的
Good.A couple of honest people.
很好 有几个诚实的人
Evolutionarily,that's the correct answer.
从进化的角度来看 这个答案是正确的
But,so,but very few of you.
但很少人举起手
Now raise your hand if you would not date somebody
那些发现约会对象没有幽默感以后
because you found out they had no sense of humor at all?
就不和他们约会的同学 请举起手来
Almost everyone -
几乎所有人都举了
maybe that's just more socially acceptable answer to do
也许是因为这个答案更为社会所接受
and that might screw the study itself.
这样可能会把研究都搞砸了
But the fact is
事实是
I think a lot of us are being honest that we really want sexual,
我认为很多人都没有说谎 我们确实想要性感的…
we really want sense of humor to be part of our mate.Good.
我们确实想要有幽默感的伴侣 好的
You know that it's just gonna happen now over and over again.
我还会一次又一次地口误
So what we find in these individuals is that
我们发现在这些人身上
if you are faced with a threat in the wild like a lion,
如果你在野外遇到危险 例如遇到狮子
you know,you want to be able to fight it or flee.
你想打赢它 或者逃跑
You don't want to tell the knock-knock joke,right?
你不会想说那个敲门笑话 对吧?
That doesn't increase your slight of adaptivity
幽默并不能增加你
of natural selection,right?
对自然选择的适应性 对吧?
But what we find is people seem to absolutely favor this.
但我们发现 人们似乎都很喜欢幽默
And there's some difference in terms of genders,
不同性别的幽默是不同的
part of what scientists and psychologists believe
科学家和心理学家认为
is that humor is a signal of cognitive fitness,
幽默是表示认知能力良好的一个信号
that just like we want physical fitness in somebody else,
就像我们喜欢别人有良好的体格一样
so too we want cognitive fitness.
我们也喜欢良好的认知能力
We want somebody humorous to view the world from different lenses
我们喜欢能用不同视角看世界的幽默之人
It actually has a dramatic effect upon not only the way that
它不仅能极大地影响
they can deal with reality
他们看待世界的方式
but the way they can help you deal with reality.
还会影响他们帮助你应付现实的方式
All those benefits we just talked about
我们刚才所说的这些
in terms of the physical benefits of humor are all garnered
幽默对生理的益处 都会出现在
by people that are surrounded by people that are laughing
那些与笑的人为伴
or they are making the jokes themselves.
或者与开玩笑的人为伴的人身上
So if you are around somebody that is funny,
如果你与幽默的人为伴
you get all those positive benefits as well.
你就能得到所有这些益处
In addition,they found a couple of interesting differences -
除此以外 他们还发现了几个有趣的差别
the differences between men and women
男人与女人的差别
by a guy named or a woman named Bressler.
这是由一个叫Bressler研究员发现的
I'm not sure which one.
我不知道这个人是男还是女的
The differences between men women by Bressler is that
Bressler发现男女的差别是
they found there's difference in terms of
他们发现男女所寻求的幽默
what people are actually looking for.
是有差别的
And they just check people flirting at bar.
他们观察在酒吧里调情的人
So the experiment was they watch people
在这个实验里 他们看
while they are flirting at the bar - this is just creepy.
那些在酒吧里调情的人 很怪
And what they would do is they make tick marks
每次女人或男人笑时
every time the female or the male would laugh.
他们就会打一个勾
And then afterwards they would go up
然后 他们会走过去
and give these two strangers a report
给这两个陌生男女一份报告
and ask them to fill out a report
让他们填完这份报告
and exchange before they go somewhere else.
并且在他们离开前 互换报告
And so what they found is that the number of laughs
他们发现女人笑的次数
by the female correlated with how much the female like the male
与女人喜欢男人的的程度成正比
and that in exchange.
反过来也是
They also found out that the number of laughs by the female
他们还发现 女人笑的次数
correlated with how much the male liked her.
与男人喜欢她的程度成正比
What they found is the male's laughter had absolutely no effect
他们还发现 男人的笑
whatsoever upon the attractiveness of either people.
对两个人的吸引力都没有任何影响
So it seems like and this would be -
似乎这…
this is an aggregate but not necessarily case for everyone.
这只是从总体来看 不是每个人都会这样
Part of what you are seeing
大家从中看到
is in trends which some people seem to be the joke generator,
一个趋势 有些人似乎是说笑话的人
as some people seem to be the joke receivers.
有些人似乎是听笑话的人
And I think it's interesting to think about
这给了我们一个很有趣的想法
where you lie in that match in terms of which one
在这两者当中 你会选择当哪一个
you are actually attempting to do with your own humor style.
当你想用你的幽默风格来吸引对方时
We also find that it's extremely important
我们还发现
in terms of the negotiations in marriage,
在婚姻谈判中 幽默很重要的
which are usually just basically the same thing.
基本上和上面那个一样
John Gottman found that - John Gottman is the guy,
John Gottman发现…John Gottman就是那个
this relationship expert who did the Four Horsemen -
恋爱专家 他做了四骑士实验
we talked about it earlier in the relationship section.
我们在之前讲爱情的课上就已经讲过了
He says that the greatest way to defuse a conflict
他说消除冲突的最佳方法
that is occurring in a negotiation or in a marriage problem,
如果在谈判中出现冲突 或者婚姻出现问题时
the greatest solution is to find a way to use humor
最佳方法就是换一个角度 把幽默
as a coping mechanism.
当作应付机制
To answer that humor in - while you are feeling stress response
要回答幽默在…当你出现应激反应
or the release of cortisol that I talked about.
或者说像我之前说的那个 皮质醇被释放出来
Even John Gottman views the humor
即使John Gottman也把幽默视为
as one of the most important ways of effectiveness.
达到效果的最重要方法
This is the... This is just interesting
这个…这个很有趣
but not related to what I'm talking about.
但和我现在讲的内容没什么关系
This is the Cthis is what brain looks like with the,
当我们叫一个大学男生想着爱时
part of the brain activated most
他的大脑就是这样子的
when a college male student is thinking about love.
大脑有些地方亮起来了
It's beautiful.
很漂亮
The rest lights up when you ask them to think about sex.
如果你叫他们想着性 剩下的地方都会亮起来
Humor as therapy - I'm just talk about this really quickly,
幽默作为一种治疗手段 我简单地讲一下这点
because I want to get onto the most powerful part of humor.
因为我想等一下讲幽默的最强大功效
Pennebaker's studies
Pennebaker的研究
which we talked about earlier about journaling said that
我们之前讲写日记的时候讲过
as you start to journal,
当你开始写日记时
you see a spike in your neural activity levels.
你的神经活动水平会出现峰值
We actually feel more stress when you are journaling,
其实你写日记的时候 感受到的压力会更大
but then afterwards,deep down to a lower restate.
但写完后 就会回落到一个低很多的水平
The same is true with humor.Humor-
幽默也是一样
because it crosses the line also increases our stress momentarily
因为幽默过界了 它暂时增加了我们的压力
but allow us to return back down to a state
但能让我们回落到
that is below or a lower restate,
一个更低的水平
because it activate our parasympathetic nervous system.
因为它激活了我们的副交感神经系统
As a result of that,
因此
humor can be a very effective way for us to use,
在一个心理治疗中
to deal with therapeutic situations.
幽默是我们可以利用的有效工具
Some of the ways that people do it are laughing groups in India,
印度有些大笑互助组就是用这个方法
where they had people get in a circle
他们会让人围成一圈
and put their heads on each other's stomachs.
把头放到另一个人的腹部上
And one person starts to go "Ha!" And another person go "Ha ha!"
一个人开始叫"哈" 另一个人也叫"哈"
And they'll do this all around the circle
整个圈的人都这样做
till everyone was laughing spontaneously.
直到所有人都自发地笑起来
And it's a great workout.
这是一种很好的健身运动
And at the end of it,you actually feel like your well being
做完以后 你会觉得自己
is so much higher at the end.
健康了很多
They also have something called cuddle bunnies,cuddle parties.
他们还有"抱抱兔子" 或者"抱抱组"
Cuddle bunnies - that's from the Ladder Theory online
抱抱免子 这是从网上的梯子理论上找来的
if you want to google that.
大家想了解的话 就去搜索一下
Cuddle parties is something that's in New York
抱抱组 是在纽约的
that I don't have time to talk about.
我没有时间讲了
And transforming trauma and bad days -
这些小组能改变心理创伤和坏心情…
I think that one of the really interesting parts of it too
我想这当中很有趣的一点是
is humor actually allows us to be able to transform things that
幽默真的可以让我们能够对我们以前认为是
we thought were negative or bad or upsetting in the past.
消积的 不好的或者让人烦恼的事情改观
And I want to talk about that as the greatest power of humor,
这就是我想说的 幽默最强大的功效
but before we do that,I want to say
但在讲这点之前 我想说
six ways you can actually increase your humor levels as well.
可以增加我们幽默感的六种方法
First of all,we just talked about one of these.
首先 我们刚才已经讲了一个了
But journaling stories that are unique to you,
把只属于你的故事写进日记了
finding funny stories that
找出你日常生活中
just as you have to go through your day and when you journal,
好笑的故事 当你写日记时
try to write about positive experiences,
要尽量写积极的经历
you are scanning your environment for the events
你要审视你的周围
that occur in your day which are positive.
找出日常生活中发生的积极事件
So too you can do that with humor and train that as a skill
想培养幽默 也可以用这个方法 把它练成一种技能
just as gratitude you can train as a skill of optimism
就像把感恩练成一种培养乐观心态的技能
So what you do is you go through your day,
你要做的是 回忆起这一天
write down something that happened during your day,
写下这一天发生的事情
then play around with it,change the shape of it,
然后拿它发挥 给它变形
keep orienting it
改变它的方向
until you can find something that is humorous about it,
直到你能从中发现一些幽默
just as Jon Stewart's writers do
就像Jon Stewart的编剧
when they are looking at the news.
看报纸上的新闻一样
As a result of that,your brain actually gets in the pattern,
结果 你的大脑会养成一种模式
the pattern of looking for things that are funny in your life.
找到生活中好笑的事情的模式
Second is watching funny people
第二个方法是观察幽默的人
when you observe other people that are funny
当你观察幽默的人时
because of these mirror neurons,
因为镜像神经元
you actually pick up the rhythm of humor from them.
你能从他们身上学到幽默的一些规律
But there is actually a rhythm you can actually study online
网上还有这样的规律供你学习
if you are interested about this.
如果你对此感兴趣的话
A rhythm of humor that you can study and that's the reason
你可以学习幽默的规律 这就是为什么
why patterns and breaking patterns is so important.
培养模式和打破模式这么重要
Be consciously,unconsciously pick those up,
有意识或无意识地学习这些规律
just as the visualization practices we were talking about,
就是我们以前讲过的可视法练习
where if you watch somebody on television who is bad at sport,
你在电视上看不擅长运动的人
if you watch them,
如果你看他们
you actually become bad at that technique as well;
你也会变得不擅长于运动
so too if you watch them who is good at this sport,
所以如果你看擅长于运动的人
you become better at the action at watching.
你会变得擅长于你看的这种运动
The same occurs when you are watching humor.
当你观察幽默时 会有同样的结果
Also is the Two question - TQP - the Two question process:
还有一个方法是TQP 两问处理法
why am I so funny? Why don't other people recognize this?
为什么我这么幽默?为什么别人没有发现我很幽默?
Keep repeating this to yourself
不断地这么问自己
and it absolutely builds your self-esteem.
绝对能提升你的自尊
In addition,the permission to be subhuman.
除此以外 还要允许自己当一个次等人类
Part of what we are seeing and Bergson talks about is that
我们和伯格森都认为
in order to make those jokes
要说这些笑话
and laugh at the things are traumatic,
对着很创伤的事笑出来
we have to have a momentary anesthesia in our heart.
我们要暂时地麻醉我们的心
The momentary anesthesia at the heart.
暂时地麻醉我们的心
And if we don't allow ourselves to be subhuman for a moment,
如果我们不允许自己当一会次等人类
we don't allow ourselves to be human and in fact,
就等于我们不允许自己有人类的缺点
to recognize that we have these id impulses.
就是不承认我们有本我冲动
Variety and breaking patterns.
多找点花样 打破模式
The more you can break a pattern,
你打破模式的次数越多
the more you are able to see potentialities within a situation.
你就越能看到一个情况里的可能性
There's a study with mice where they have...
有一个用老鼠来做的实验
If you have one mice,mouse in the cage,
把一只老鼠放进笼子里
they will have sex with a female mouse
让它和一只母老鼠性交
you put in the cage like 2 or 3 times
当你把它放进笼子两到三次后
and then it gets really tired.
它就会变得很累
And then it goes off to a corner and doesn't want to cuddle.
它就会躲到角落里 不想和母老鼠拥抱
And it does this about 10 minutes - this is called latency period
它会维持这样10分钟 这叫做潜伏期
where biologically you can't have sex for a while
这时候你生理上无法进行性行为
because it's too tired.
因为太累了
And next of course you introduce a new female into the cage,
接下来 放一只新的母老鼠进笼子里
at this point,
这时候
the mouse goes over and continue this experiment again
老鼠会走过去 继续做这个实验
regardless of the amount of the latency period is there.
不管有没有过潜伏期
What this seems to indicate is that our brains,
这个实验说明了 我们的大脑
our mammalian brains are actually hardwired for variety,
我们哺乳动物的大脑天生就要寻找多样性的
and that's not an appropriate approach to relationships
这不是谈恋爱的好方法
but that's when we recognize
但这时我们会认识到
that variety is absolutely the spice of life:
花样是生活的调味剂
the more you can change up the patterns you are doing,
你越是改变你现在的模式
the more you see potentials in your environment.
你就越能看到环境中的可能性
And the Tetris effect which we already talked about.
我们之前讲过的俄罗斯方块效应
So now for the greatest power of humor,
现在来讲幽默的最大功效
which I think is really important.
我认为这点很重要
I want to talk a little bit and show a little clip,
我想讲一下 然后让大家看一段视频
since we just have 6 minutes left.
因为我们只剩六分钟了
I want to show you a clip that I found to be extremely powerful.
我想让大家看一段我觉得很有强大的视频
I don't think it's a buzz-kill after having a humor lecture.
我不觉得上了一节幽默课后 看这段视频会坏了大家的心情
But I think it's really important to see
但我觉得它很重要 值得我们一看
how Jon Stewart dealt with September 11th tragedy afterwards.
这段视频是关于Jon Stewart在911悲剧后怎么做节目的
I think just from the psychological perspective,it's not funny.
我觉得从心理研究的角度来看 它不好笑
But watch what's happening to him.
但大家注意他的变化
Watch his facial expressions,as he is attempting -
观察他的脸部表情 看他怎样试图
this almost heroic attempt to bring humor back in the situation.
在这种情况下把幽默带回节目的壮举
And listen how he describes humor.
听听他是怎么形容幽默的
We'll watch this for 3 minutes,
这段我们会看三分钟
watch 1 minute of Family Guy clip.
然后看一段一分钟的"恶搞之家"
And then I'll conclude in 1 minute.
然后我会用一分钟进行总结
Wait for it.
等等
[VIDEO: JON STEWART "THE DAILY SHOW WITH JON STEWART,
视频：JON STEWART
Taired on September 20,2001]
2001年9月20日
Jon Stewart:Good evening and welcome to "The Daily Show."
晚上好 欢迎收看"今日秀"
We are back.
我们又开播了
This is our first show since the tragedy in New York City.
这是自从纽约发生悲剧以来 我们播出的第一集节目
And there is no other way really to start this show
要开始这集节目 真的没有别的方式
than to ask you at home the question that
只有问各位家庭观众一个问题
we've asked the audience here tonight
这个问题我们已经问过今晚的现场观众
and that we've asked everybody that we know here in New York
自911以来 我们已经问过我们认识的
since September 11th,and that is,"Are you okay?"
每一个纽约人 这个问题是"你还好吗?"
We pray that you are and that your family is.
我们祈祷大家都安好 大家的家人都安好
I'm sorry to do this to you.
很抱歉要对你们做这种事
It's another entertainment show beginning
这又是一个娱乐节目
with an overwrought speech of a shaken host.
一个惊魂未定的主持 念着一段过分矫饰的开场白
TV is nothing,if not redundant.
电视节目除了多余 就真的什么都不是了
So,I apologize for that.
我为此向大家道歉
It's something that unfortunately,
但很不幸
we do for ourselves so that we can drain whatever abscess
我们必须为自己这么做 这样我们才能抽干
is in our hearts and move onto the business of making you laugh,
心里的脓 继续我们的工作 逗大家笑
which we haven't been able to do very effectively lately.
最近我们都很难笑得出来了
Everyone's checked in already,I know we're late.
大家都来上班了 我知道我们晚了
I'm sure we're getting in right under the wire
我知道我们开播的时间刚刚好
before the cast of "Survivor" offers their insight
赶在了"幸存者"剧组出来建议
into what to do in these situations.
我们在这种情况下应该怎么做之前
They said to get back to work.
他们的建议就是 回去工作
And there were no jobs available for a man in the fetal position
对于一个抱成一团 躲在桌子下哭的男人来说
under his desk crying,which I gladly would have taken.
是很难找到工作的 找得到的话我会很乐意去做
So I come back here.
所以我回来了
Tonight's show is obviously not a regular show.
很显然今晚的节目不是一集平常的节目
We looked through the vaults,
我们翻遍了资料库
we found some clips that we thought might make you smile,
找了几段我们觉得能逗你们笑的视频
which is really what's necessary,I think,right about now.
我觉得在现在这是非常有必要的
A lot of folks have asked me,
很多人问过我
"What are you going to do when you get back?
"你上班后 怎么做这个节目?
What are you going to say?"
你会说什么?"
I mean,Jeez,what a terrible thing to have to do.
我是说 天啊 这种时候拍这样的节目多么不合适
I don't see it as a burden at all.I see it as a privilege.
我不觉得这是一个负担 我觉得这是一个荣幸
I just see it as a privilege and everyone here does.
我觉得这是一个荣幸 这里的每个人都这么觉得
Shawn Achor:Am I back on? I think that's such a powerful clip.
听到我了吗?我觉得这是一段很强有力的视频
And you can deal -
你可以…
hear him dealing with the suffering that he is experiencing.
听到他内心正在痛苦地挣扎
And you could see him trying to jump start the humor
你可以看到他试图说几句笑
and recoiling back again.
然后又退缩回去了
You can hear him talking about those idioms he imposes
你可以听到他讲他惯用的语言风格
that he needs to release,
他需要释放的感情
and later goes on and talks about the frustration.
然后说他的挫败感
At the end of the show,
这集节目的最后
he actually just brings out a puppy on the stage
他带了一只小狗上台
and he just allows the puppy to be there to trying to get us,
他就让小狗留在台上 试图让我们
to just return to this point where we can see potentials
恢复心情 让我们看到
beyond the tragedy that was actually faced upon them.
在眼前的悲剧以外 还是有很多可能性的
But I think it's just a remarkable scene to watch.
我觉得这是一段很优秀的视频 值得一看
But afterwards you could see the people afterwards
过后 你可以看到人们
were dealing with the tragedy in different ways.
用不同的方法应付悲剧
I think one of the things that was very interesting from
我觉得从一个社会学角度来看
a sociological perspective was Family Guy's response to this,
"恶搞之家"对911事件的回应也很有趣
where they are going through this period
他们经历的那段时间
where we were absolutely terrified of people
我们都很害怕
making terrorist threats against United States and they show this
用恐怖主义威胁美国的人 但他们却拍了这么一估
[VIDEO: FAMILY GUY Season 4 Episode 14]
视频：恶搞之家 第四季 14集
(Somewhere in Afghanistan)
(阿富汗某个地方)
Osama Bin Laden:This is a message to all American infidels.
所有美国异教徒听好了
Prepare to die in a sea of holy fire.
准备在圣火的包围中死去吧
You will be punished for your decadent ways
你们将会为你们的堕落受到惩罚
on the first day of Radaman.
就在拉达曼的第一天
You...(laughing) Wait,wait a minute.
你…等等
Did I just say? What did I say...Radaman?
我刚才说什么了拉达曼?
Bla-bla-bla.Ra-ma-dan.
啦啦啦 拉-达-曼
Radaman...What is that?
拉达曼 是什么?
Yeah,maybe Dennis Radaman (Rodman)
对 可能丹尼斯・拉达曼(应该是罗德曼)
is gonna punish you with his crazy hair.
会用他的怪头发惩罚你
No.What's that?
不 你说啥?
Right.Right.Yeah.
对 好的
Okay,okay,all right,okay,let's go again.
好了 好了 我们再来一次
Okay.This is a message to all amer...
好的 所有美国人听好了
I'm not...I'm not going to be able to do it now.I'm not gonna...
我现在拍不了 我要…
Okay,all right,no.
好了 不
No,I-I got to get all the,I got to get all the laughs out.
不 我要…我要先笑个饱
Okay,I got to get all the laughs out.
好了 我要先笑个饱
Lalala.Lulululu.Okay,all right.
好了 行了
Today,sometime.Stop making that face over there!
今天 有时 你别再做鬼脸了
What are you doing? I can't...
你在干什么?我不能…
He makes that face and it makes me laugh.
他在做鬼脸 害得我要笑
Okay,you know what? Just turn around.Turn...turn around.
好了 不如这样 你转过身 转过身
I don't care where you look.Just look over there,okay.
我不管你面朝哪里 朝那边吧 好的
All right,they're cracking.They're cracking up over there.
好了 他们在那边大笑起来
Okay.Oh,yeah,yeah,look who's snickering over there,Mr.
好了 看看谁又在那边偷笑了
"I can't do a suicide bombing because I'm sick."
"我不能去做自杀式爆炸 因为我病了"先生
He had a,he had a note...He had a note from his doctor! [Laugh]
他…他还有医生签的请假条
Shawn Achor:He said he had a note from his doctor.
他还有医生签的请假条
I'm gonna cut it off there,cause it's getting worse.
下面的不看了 因为越来越不好笑了
I just have one minute left.
我只剩一分钟
So I just wanna tell you this
我想告诉大家
and I think that the things we've been talking about today,
我们今天讲的一些内容
I think that's a remarkable scene.
我觉得这是一段很好的视频
And what you see as we are moving from something that
大家看到 当我们从吓到我们的情况下走出来
we are terrified of to something that we can begin to laugh at,
并且拿这样的事来开玩笑
because we can see the humanity there.
因为我们能看到当中的人性
We can see ourselves laughing and making mistakes
我们能看到自己大笑
while giving a video taped conference.
拍视频会议时犯错
Now not necessarily on the same topic that he was doing.
不一定是拍他说的那种话
But the things we talk about today
我们今天讲的内容是
is that humor is like optimism,
幽默就像乐观主义
is a lens through which we view the world
我们透过它来看世界
that demands a mindfulness to potentials,
它需要我们用正念来找到可能性
that increases our health,our social benefits,
它能加强我们的健康 改善我们的社交
and our physical benefits,
和我们的身体
and they can serve as a therapeutic process.
它能作为一种心理治疗方法
I think the humor itself we perceive to be a luxury
我们把幽默视为一个奢侈
but I think in times the suffering and conflict
但我认为在痛苦和冲突
and tragedy and recession and depression C
悲剧 经济倒退 大萧条出现的时候…
I think there's nothing more important than humor.
我想没什么会比幽默更重要的
And it's just an honor like Jon Stewart said,
就像Jon Stewart说的 能给你们上课
to be here with you today.
是我的荣幸
Thank you.
谢谢
[Applause and cheers]
掌声